<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse, of marriage and vviuing and of the greatest mystery therein contained: how to choose a good wife from a bad. An argument of the dearest vse, but the deepest cunning that man may erre in: which is, to cut by a thrid betweene the greatest good or euill in the world. Pertinent to both sexes, and conditions, as well those already gone before, as shortly to enter this honest society. By Alex. Niccholes, Batchelour in the art he neuer yet put in practise.</title>
            <author>Niccholes, Alexander.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08179</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18514</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113190</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848428</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848428</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13521</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08179)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13521)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 967:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse, of marriage and vviuing and of the greatest mystery therein contained: how to choose a good wife from a bad. An argument of the dearest vse, but the deepest cunning that man may erre in: which is, to cut by a thrid betweene the greatest good or euill in the world. Pertinent to both sexes, and conditions, as well those already gone before, as shortly to enter this honest society. By Alex. Niccholes, Batchelour in the art he neuer yet put in practise.</title>
                  <author>Niccholes, Alexander.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by N[icholas] O[kes] for Leonard Becket, and are to be sold at his shop in the Inner-Temple,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of marriage and vviuing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13521:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13521:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Diſcourſe, OF MARRIAGE AND WIVING: AND OF The greateſt Myſtery therein CONTAINED: How to chooſe a good Wife from a bad.</p>
            <p>An Argument Of the deareſt vſe, but the deepeſt cunning that man may erre in: which is, to cut by a Thrid betweene the greateſt Good or euill in the world.</p>
            <p>Pertinent to both Sexes, and Conditions, as well thoſe already gone before, as ſhortly to enter this honeſt ſociety.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Amare &amp; ſapere vix Dijs conceditur.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>BY ALEX. NICCHOLES, Batchelour in the Art he neuer yet put in practiſe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Hee that ſtands by, and doth the game ſuruey,</l>
               <l>Sees more oftimes then thoſe that at it play.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>N.O.</hi> for <hi>Leonard Becket,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in the Inner-Temple. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13521:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13521:2"/>
            <head>TO THE VERTV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVS YONG GENTLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAN, AND HIS VVORTHILY RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected friend, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Edgworth,</hi> vnder Treaſurer of Windſor, Health and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in his owne Perſon, and in the happy fruition of his vertuous Wife.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, your felicity, the higheſt top of enioyment in this kind, is become the aime, that the practicke Art in this ſchoole of direction leuelleth at, you being already inſtated (with enuy and admiration) in that bliſſe, which others may thus toyle after in moſt beſeeming circumſtances (by many degrees) to come ſhort of: VVhen I enter this courſe of life (as, for ought I know, I may one day marry) be it my higheſt ambition, with all my directions, to haue one to be a neere imitator of her ſo many Religious and Morall vertues, for whoſe happy continuance my beſt wiſhes ſhall be ſpent, that ſhe may long continue yours, to make you a father of happy and vndoubted children;
<pb facs="tcp:13521:3"/>
ſonnes for the earth, and Saints for heauen, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying vpon your head all the comforts in that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant: And for this Treatiſe, which, by your dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, comes forth to direct others to that modell of happineſſe wherein you ſtand eminent, may it haue that ſucceſſe with all, that it hath had approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with you, and as kinde entertainement with the world as thoſe beſt creatures, the ſubiect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in their perfection deſerue, which are the Seed and Seminary thereof, and which (by this meanes) haue maintained that laſting, and yet vn-ended, war againſt thoſe two arch, and vnwearied aduerſaries of Mankind <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> the waſters thereof, and conſumers of all ſublunary things, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan their ſiege againſt the firſt man that liued, and haue euer ſince held on without league, or impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, for the ſpace of theſe 5500 yeares and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and which ſhall go on and continue the ſiedge to the end thereof, and conſummation of all things: VVherein if it ſhall be ſo happy (beyond expectation) the paine thereof hath beene well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, and your encouragement fortunately ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded, which howſoeuer I leaue it to the aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and you to your hearts beſt wiſhes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By him that intirely is dedicated yours:</hi> ALEX. NICCHOLES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:13521:3"/>
            <head>To the Youth and Batchelary of <hi>England, hote blouds at high Reuels,</hi> which fore-thought of this action, and all other, that hereafter intend this aduenture.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>INCE that the meaneſt bleſsing in mans life,</l>
            <l>Is not the Dowry of a vertuous wife;</l>
            <l>No otherwiſe then is the aduerſe croſſe,</l>
            <l>To him that beares it the moſt eaſy loſſe.</l>
            <l>Therefore to you, whoſe weary bonds yet keepe,</l>
            <l>Seuering the Armes wherein you long to ſleepe;</l>
            <l>That haue before-hand, many a tedious howre,</l>
            <l>Wiſht that approaching minute in your powre,</l>
            <l>Which when arriu'd, moſt ſlowly brought to paſſe,</l>
            <l>Cancels but Parchment to inroule in Braſſe:</l>
            <l>What not ſo ſhort a terme of yeares ſhall end,</l>
            <l>Vnleſſe one ſhew himſelfe the kinder friend:</l>
            <l>Wherein, leſt your to forward haſt ſhould ſtray,</l>
            <l>Here is beforehand chalked out a way:</l>
            <l>(As conſcience craueth, for ſo large connexion</l>
            <l>Should not be entred in without direction.)</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13521:4"/>Which who ſo walkes in to the true intent,</l>
            <l>Shall not commit that action to repent.</l>
            <l>The ignorant by this haue ſharper eyes,</l>
            <l>More deeper inſight to theſe miſteries,</l>
            <l>And were their vnderſtanding darke or blinde,</l>
            <l>To paſſe this Laborinth 'tis here refinde:</l>
            <l>Here are the Characters inſculpt and read,</l>
            <l>That make a happy or a loathed bed.</l>
            <l>What woman is on whom all theſe depend,</l>
            <l>Her <hi>Vſe, Creation, Excellence,</hi> and <hi>End.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In making choyce how much to be confin'd,</l>
            <l>To <hi>Beauty, Riches, Parentage,</hi> or <hi>Kinde:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>What are the chiefe diſturbers of this ſtate,</l>
            <l>That ſooneſt point a man that ſoreſt fate.</l>
            <l>Here are the Rockes diſcouered to the eye,</l>
            <l>That he that would not ſhipwracke may ſaile by.</l>
            <l>And theſe the rather being aforehand laid,</l>
            <l>Vnballanſt pleaſures to each youth and maid,</l>
            <l>That when experience ſhall their ſweetneſſe tell,</l>
            <l>In ſtead of heauen they purchaſe not a hell.</l>
            <l>And that the ioy their forward youth hath ſought,</l>
            <l>Vncroſly match'd mry come more neere their thought.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">To thoſe that forbeare mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage for more liberty of ſin.</note>But you whoſe luſts this lymit ſhall not tye,</l>
            <l>For more inlargement to variety,</l>
            <l>That will not any your owne proper call,</l>
            <l>The better interreſſed to commerſe with all.</l>
            <l>As when your Lord and Lady downe are laid,</l>
            <l>Behind the dore to woe the Chamber-maid:</l>
            <l>Or amongſt neighbours, where you lead your liues,</l>
            <l>To be the more familliar with ther wiues,</l>
            <l>Or any place where ere you do eſpye,</l>
            <l>A pretty morſell pleaſing to your eye,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13521:4"/>To ceize it more ſuſpectleſſe, being knowne</l>
            <l>Then hee that hath at home a wife of's owne.</l>
            <l>Well take that bleſsing, but withall this curſe,</l>
            <l>To walke on weake legges with an empty purſe.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:13521:5"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 OF the Inſtitution and Author of Marriage.</item>
               <item>2 Of the excellency of Marriage with the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and vſe.</item>
               <item>3 Worldly choyce what it is, or how, for the moſt part, men chooſe theis wiues.</item>
               <item>4 How to chooſe a good wife from a bad.</item>
               <item>5 What yeares are moſt conuenient for Marriage.</item>
               <item>6 That conueniency and fitneſſe in choyce, is more to bee preferred then either Beauty, Riches, or any other addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of either minde, or fortune.</item>
               <item>7 What is that chiefe moath and canker, that eſpecially vndermineth, and fretteth the marriage bed.</item>
               <item>8 Aduice for choyce, and whether it be beſt to marry a Widdow, or a Maide.</item>
               <item>9 Since the end of Marriage is Iſſue, whether it be lawfull for old Couples to marry, that are paſt hope of children.</item>
               <item>10 The difference betweene Luſt and Loue.</item>
               <item>11 The beſt way to continue a woman chaſte.</item>
               <item>12 The patterne of a bad huſband, and a good wife, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced in two letters.</item>
               <item>13 An admonition to Hu-bands and Wiues, for Vnity and Concord.</item>
               <item>14 Certaine precepts to be obſerued in Wiuing and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, as alſo reſolutions to Chaſtety.</item>
               <item>15 Diſcontents in all Ages, Sexes, States, Conditions.</item>
            </list>
            <q>
               <l>If by this leuell thou a good wife hit,</l>
               <l>Thanke God that ere this Booke was bought, or writ.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13521:5"/>
            <head>Of Marriage and Wiuing.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. Of the firſt Inſtitution and Authour of Marriage.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not good for man to bee alone</hi> (ſaith the alone and abſolute Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all goodneſſe it ſelfe) <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ergo adiutorem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Let vs therefore make him a helper meete for him:</hi> So the creation of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was to be a helper to the man, not a hinderer, a companion for his comfort, not a vexation to his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, for <hi>Conſortium eſt Solatium,</hi> Company is comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble though neuer ſo ſmall, and <hi>Adam</hi> tooke no little ioy in this his ſingle companion, being thereby fréed from that ſolitude and ſilence which his loneneſſe would elſe haue bene ſubiect vnto, had there beene no other end nor vſe in her more, then this her bare preſence and ſociety alone: But beſides all this, the earth is large and muſt be peopled, and therefore they are now the Crowne of his Worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, the laſt and beſt and perfecteſt peece of his handi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke diuided into Genders, as the reſt of His creatures are, <hi>Male</hi> and <hi>Female,</hi> fit and enabled <hi>Procreare ſibi ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> to bring forth their like, to accompliſh his will, who thus bleſſed their fruitfulneſſe in the Bud: <hi>Increaſe &amp; mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply, and repleniſh the earth.</hi> Well might S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing this, <hi>Marriage is honorable amongſt al men, &amp; the bed vndefiled;</hi> ſince God himſelfe was the Author and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutor
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13521:6"/>
thereof euen in Paradice, who gaue the woman in the in, before in his ſleepe <hi>Adam</hi> loſt a <hi>Rib,</hi> but now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Reperit Coſtam,</hi> he hath his Rib againe with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> encreaſe, branched into many <hi>Veines</hi> and <hi>Ribs,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <hi>Arteries,</hi> of wonderfull vſe, and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. So the creation of woman as it was for man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> out of man; <hi>Adam</hi> was made of the ſame of the earth, and were it not to make woman proud, I would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> was of that better ſubſtance, of that well huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded workeman-ſhip, and refined matter, refined and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by the touch of his hands, in moulding to ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llent a proportion as man, of a bone taken out of his ſide (which that ſide euer wanteth ſince as Anatomiſts ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue) to make him the more plyable towards her; not of a bone of his foote, that ſhe ſhould be ſo low or contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or of his head, ſo high or ambitious, but of his ſide, a middle part, that ſhee might bee of a middle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, his fellow and companion, not his ſeruant or ſlaue, for <hi>Socij ſunt qui iunguntur lateribus,</hi> they are fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes that walke ſide by ſide: of a bone neare to his heart, to put him in minde of dilection and loue; from vnder his arme of protection and defence, &amp;c. Now the Author of this creation we finde here to be the Author of this Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; He who made the woman of the man gaue her to the man, euen God himſelfe, who as <hi>Caſſianus</hi> ſaith further, in the very prime and beginning of the world, <hi>Dedit,</hi> this <hi>Vnam Vni,</hi> gaue this one woman to one man, and no more then one, although for the increaſe and peopling of all the yet vnhabited Regions and Kingdomes of the earth: In which, no doubt, the Diuine Wiſedome had a reſpect to the loue, not to the luſt of man; aiming hereby to aduance the one, and ſuppreſſe the other, for where loue is diuided there it is weakned, can neuer be ſtrong, and as we ſee by experience, he who loues many formally neuer loues any feruently, for vnity is loues number, cannot tranſcend, and God would haue an entire affection be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13521:6"/>
the huſband and the wife, which he himſelfe in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thus vouchſafed to honor by coniunction, that as the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e bodies were then not two, ſo their deſires ſhould be but one, and withall to inſinuate by this his proper inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the more reſpect and reuerence to that holy ordination, which had ſo high a beginning and ſo holy an end, honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by his Perſon, by his Prophets, by his Miracles, and which ſhould ſo generally be exerciſed, throughout all eſtates and conditions, ages and times, to the end of the world, and deciſtency of all things, which by this meanes (ere that eternall diſſolution) ſhould runne a long and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued race in deſpight of graue and death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. Of the execellency of Marriage, with the conſequence and vſe thereof.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE excellency thereof doth the more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt it ſelfe in this, in that it was an addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of beatitude and bleſſedneſſe, to that happy and abſolute eſtate that <hi>Adam</hi> had in his firſt creation and innocency, that it was ſo pretious flower that it would not thriue but in ſo pure a ſoyle, that God himſelfe was the Authour to inſtitute it, and the Prieſt to celebrate it, ere euer ſinne and impurity had tainted the earth, or blemiſhed the Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall beauty of either the Bride or Bridegroome; and though the conſequence in that place brought ſorrow and death, yet hath it a relation to as full, nay more ample ioy and life in the extent and determination thereof, then it could otherwiſe haue had in that firſt perſeuerance and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iton, from which, though now by ſinne, our beſt faculties, priuiledges and prerogatiues, in all kinds, are ſo clowded, eclypſed and fallen away, that wee diſcerne not aright the excellencies, true vſes and ends of ſo Diuine a Myſtery in it ſelfe, notwithſtanding we do yet in this twylight per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13521:7"/>
ſuch glimpſes and ſparkles of originall purity and felicity vnextinguiſhed therein, that we are wedded by our owne wils, and induced by ſo naturall a coaction to the embracement thereof for the mutuall ſociety and comfort of life, without which it could neither ſubſiſt nor conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, more then to any other duty or action therein, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded or required whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>From the excellency of the inſtitution, come wee to the excellency of the true vſe, the danger of the contrary, and therefore the deepe regard to be had before hand, as in the enterpriſe it ſelfe, being of ſuch weighty moment and import of which one thus further diſplaying it, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</p>
               <p>Marriage of all the humane actions of a mans life, is one of the greateſt weight and conſequence, as thereon depending the future good, or euill, of a mans whole after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, and dayes; that Gordian knot once faſtened not to be vnlooſed but by death, the meanes either to exalt an high to preferment, or caſt downe headlong to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the preſent diſpoſer of a mans whole eſtate and fortune to his greateſt ioy or myſery, and therefore with his <hi>tale pondus,</hi> (as before) not be danced into lightly or vnaduiſedly, with the firſt that comes to hand, as a blind man layes his hold, but ſoberly entered vpon with mature aduiſe, yeares, and deliberation, conſent, and counſell of Parents and Friends: For it is in this action as in a Stratageme of warre: <hi>Wherein he that erres can erre but once, periſheth vnrecouerably to all after aduice and reliefe:</hi> And therefore that merry prouerbe is not amiſſe, that thus implyeth; That in <hi>Wiuing</hi> and <hi>Thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,</hi> a man ſhould aſke counſell of all the world, it being a matter of ſuch difficulty, doubt, and danger to bee reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in; ſuch a continuall ſtorme and tempeſt to thoſe that lanch not forth in a proſperous gale, hauing peruerted their felicity therein by running from the rule of God in their choyce, that (with <hi>Ionas</hi>) ſuch to be deliuered, were
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13521:7"/>
better be caſt aliue into the Sea, to the belly of the Whale, and mercy of the mercileſſe bottomleſſe deepe (though with him they neuer came to ſhoare againe) then indure ſuch a perpetuall vexation it is the harbenger vnto, with ſuch a <hi>Leuiathan</hi> of the Land as is a furious woman: for as a vertuous woman is a hauen of beauty, ſo a wicked woman is a ſea of euils, and in her tyde more full then that element of monſters, worſe far to liue with then a ſmoaky houſe, for that for the moſt part, offends onely the eyes in the head, but this all the ſences in the body: Nay, he that hath ſuch a Familiar, hath a worſe neighbour of his owne, then <hi>Horſam</hi> ſhould haue had, if her fabulous Dragon had beene true: Yet though in the curſe it be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to theſe euils, bleſſe it in the true vſe, and it is of all humane comforts the greateſt; for if the mutuall ſociety betweene friend and friend be ſo great, that in affliction it adminiſtreth comfort, and in ioy it heapeth the meaſure to the brime, by detracting from the ſowre, and adding to the ſweete, by a ſenſible participation of eithers quality, how much more then ſhall it be enlarged by ſuch a friend, which is to vs a ſecond ſelfe, or Treaſurer of our owne thoughts, and therefore more neerely interreſſed in either the one or the other.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, in thy <hi>Marriage,</hi> the very name whereof ſhould portend vnto theee <hi>Merry-age,</hi> thou not onely vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt vnto thy ſelfe a friend, and comfort for ſociety, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a companion for pleaſure, and in ſome ſort a ſeruant for profite too, for a wife is all theſe: Beſides, by the excellency and bleſſing of this inſtitution, thou continueſt thy name, thy likeneſſe, and thy Generation walkes vpon earth, and ſo liueſt in thy ſimilitude, in deſpight of death, when thou thy ſelfe art dead, and raked vp in duſt, and otherwiſe without remembrance, vnleſſe by ſome ruinous ſtone, or ragged Epitaph, and ſo (in ſome ſort) makeſt thy body immortall, like thy ſoule, and not onely by this doſt thou adde to the <hi>Sons of the earth,</hi> but <hi>to the Saints of heauen;</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:13521:8"/>
Beſides, by this ſo excellent, ſo honourably accounted of amongſt all men are thy wilde and vnbrideled affections reduced to humanity and ciuility, to mercy and clemency, and thou thy ſelfe called backe to looke into thy ſelfe, and to vnderſtand the ſubſtance and truth of things, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that hath no wife is ſaid to be a man vnbuilt that wanteth one of his ribbes, a ſleepe as <hi>Adam</hi> was till his wife was made, for marriage awaketh the vnderſtanding as out of a dreame; and he that hath no wife is ſaid to be a man in the midſt of the ſea, periſhing for want of this ſhip to waft him to ſhore: Is ſaid to be parched in the heate of the Sunne, that hath not this Vine to reſt him vnder her ſhadow: If ſickeneſſe come it brings thee a Phyſition; if health continue it is partly a preſeruer. But to go further, to equall it with the beſt commended Virginity, where is the man this day liuing whoſe Virginity may be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with <hi>Abrahams</hi> Mariage, in whom all the Nations of the earth were bleſſed, S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> oppoſeth it to the Virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of S. <hi>Iohn:</hi> But the greateſt authority we haue in praiſe of Marriage, is the vnion of Chriſt with his Church com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared vnto it: The Bond whereof is the holy Ghoſt, the contract the Goſpell, the Apoſtles the Regiſters, all marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, except S. <hi>Iohn</hi> and S. <hi>Paul:</hi> And Ieſus Chriſt ſealed it with his Bloud, the betrothing whereof is heere below in the Church, but the wedding it ſelfe ſhall be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnized in heauen: It is likewiſe the originall of all paires, of all couples, <hi>Primum par, fundamentum parium</hi> ſaith one, father and childe, maiſter and ſeruant, huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and wife, all grow out of this firſt vnion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction, all kindred and affinity in the world take their birth from this roote, without which men would liue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearſed like ſauage beaſts and irrationall creatures, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtinction or ſeparation of Tribe or family, which are the firſt parts of a Common-wealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:13521:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. Worldly choyce what it is, or how, for the moſt part men chooſe their wiues.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a faſhion much in vſe in theſe times to chooſe wiues as Chapmen ſell their wares, with <hi>Quantum dabitis?</hi> what is the moſt you will giue? and if their parents, or guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians ſhall reply there vertues are their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and others haue they none, let them be as dutifull as <hi>Sara,</hi> as vertuous as <hi>Anna,</hi> as obedient as the Virgine <hi>Mary;</hi> theſe to the wiſe man, euery one a rich portion, and more pretious then the gold of <hi>Ophire,</hi> ſhall be nothing valued, or make vp where wealth is wanting; theſe may be adiuncts or good additions, but money muſt be the principall, of all that marry, and (that ſcope is large) there are but few that vndergoe it for the right end and vſe, whereby it comes to paſſe that many attaine not to the bleſſedneſſe therein. Some vndergoe this curſe in ſteed of bleſſing, meerely for luſt chuſing their wiues moſt vnfitly, as Adultereſſes, and ſuch are ſaid to marry by the eye, looking no further then a carnall beauty is diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, which conſiſts in the outward ſhape and lyneaments of the body, as in gate, geſture, countenance, behauiour, &amp;c. And for ſuch a one ſo ſhe be faire, and can kiſſe, ſhe hath portion enough for ſuch a Pirate: but when this flower withers, as it is of no continuance, for diſeaſes blaſt it, age deuoures it, diſcontent doth wither it (onely vertue is not foyled by theſe aduerſaries) what ſhall continue loue as then to the end, there Winter ſure ſhall be full of want, full of diſcontent, that thus graſhopper-like reſpected their Summer: There are others that marry to ioyne wealth, to wealth, and thoſe are ſaid to marry by the fingers ends: Some others there are that take their wiues from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port or good liking of others, and thoſe are ſaid to take
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13521:9"/>
their wiues vpon truſt, and ſuch I hope are not ſeldome deceiued in their venture. There are ſome that marry for continuance of poſterity, and thoſe come neereſt to the true intent, for the end of marriage is <hi>proles,</hi> iſſue; It was the primall bleſſing, <hi>Increaſe and multiply:</hi> God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and bequeathed many Precepts and Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to mankind, yet of all that euer he deliuered, neuer was there any better obſerued (for the letter) then this: Nay, the moſt part are ſo ready to accompliſh his Will herein, that for haſt, many times, they ouerſlip the true circumſtances thereof, doing it, <hi>Propter intentionem, praeter viam,</hi> for God requires <hi>Liberi,</hi> not <hi>Spurij;</hi> children not baſtards; and thoſe that thus increaſe it, do it more for the manner then the end, more for luſt then for loue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII. How to chooſe a good wife from a bad.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His vndertaking is a matter of ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, for good wiues are many times ſo like vnto bad, that they are hardly diſcerned betwixt, they could not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe deceiue ſo many as they do, for the deuill can tranſforme himſelfe into an Angell of Light, the better to draw others into the chaines of darkeneſſe, ſo theſe, his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, themſelues into the ſhape of honeſty, the better to intangle others in the bonds of repentance: If therefore the yoke of marriage be of ſuch perpetuity, and laſting euen <hi>Vſque ad naecem,</hi> and the ioyes or grieuance thereon depending of equall continuance therwith, either to make a ſhort heauen or hell in this world, is not therefore to bee vndergone but vpon the dueſt regard, &amp; moſt aduiſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration that may be, and becauſe it is ſuch a ſea, wherein ſo many ſhipwracke for want of better knowledge and aduiſe vpon a Rock, that tooke not better counſell in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13521:9"/>
hauen, I haue therefore, in ſome ſort, to preuent this danger, erected (as it were) certaine Land-markes and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections in the way, to giue aime to ſuch paſſengers as ſhall héereafter expoſe themſelues to the mercy of this fury, and the rather becauſe our age is ſo aduenturous, whether boldnes or blindnes be their guid, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meere childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake with veſſels ſcarce capable to hoyſe vp ſayle, &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture thoſe paſſages, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former tunes in their nonage, nere preſident vs in the like, would haue thought ſcarce naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable, but many times this calme that leads them forth in a ſun-ſhine with pleaſure, brings them home in a tempeſt with ſorrow; and therefore (as I ſaid) hee that would not repent him afterwards let him be aduiſed before, for wiſe fore-ſight for the moſt part is crowned with happy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, therefore ſay not hereafter (for it is a weake reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy) <hi>Vtinam ſaperem,</hi> would God I had bene better adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but be ſo.</p>
               <p>The firſt aime that I would giue to him, that would aduenture this voyage (for marriage is an aduenture, for whoſoeuer marries aduentures, hee aduentures his peace, his freedome, his liberty, his body; yea, and ſometimes his ſoule too) is, that in his election, after hee hath made choice of his wife, which euer I would haue grounded vpon ſome of theſe promiſing likely-hoods, <hi>vid.</hi> that ſhe be of a ſober and milde aſpect, courteous behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, decent carriage, of a fixed eye, conſtant looke, and vnaffected gate, the contrary being oftentimes ſignes of ill portent and conſequence; for as the common ſaying is, an honeſt woman dwels at the ſigne of an honeſt counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and wilde lookes (for the moſt part) accompany wilde conditions; a rowling eye is not fixed, but would fixe vpon obiects it likes, it lookes for, and affected nicety is euer a ſigne of laſciuious petulancy.</p>
               <p>Next regard, according as thine eſtate and condition ſhall beſt inſtruct thee, the education, and quality, of her thou haſt ſo elected; her perſonage not being vnreſpected,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13521:10"/>
for loue lookes ſometimes as well with the eye of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as with the minde, and beauty in ſome begets affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and affection augmenteth loue, whereas the contrary would decreaſe, and diminiſh it, and ſo bring thee to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d bed, which muſt be vtterly taken heed of, for the dangerous conſequences that follow; therefore, let thy wiſedome ſo gouerne thine affection, that as it ceize not vp deformity to thine owne proper vſe, for ſome ſiniſter reſpect to be ſhortly after repented of; ſo likewiſe (for the meane is euer beſt) that it leuell not at ſo high and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute indowment and perfection, that euery carnall eye ſhall bethinke thee iniury, that euery Gotiſh diſpoſition ſhall leuell to throw open thy incloſures, that thy wife ſhall bee harder to be kept then the Garden of the <hi>Heſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rides,</hi> for as the <hi>Italian</hi> prouerbe is,
<q>
                     <l>Whoſe horſe is white, and wife is faire,</l>
                     <l>His head is neuer voide of care.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Next after thou haſt thus elected thy choyſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered her in her ſelfe, with the aforeſaid circumſtances, &amp; this one more (not being of his minde that merrily ſaid (ſpeaking of his wife) ſince he was to make choice out of things that were euill, he thought it moſt wiſedome to chooſe the leaſt) to regard that ſhee be not of too dwarfiſh a ſize, and kindred, to ſtore thee with a generation of Pigmies, dwarfes, halfe men, that want the Maieſty and power of heigth and ſtrength, and the comlineſſe a good ſtature is for the moſt part wedded vnto: After this, a little looke backe to the ſtocke from whence ſhe ſprung, for as <hi>Ezekiell</hi> ſaith, <hi>Like mother, like daughter;</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and nature approues it, that the fruite will reliſh of the Tree from whence it ſprung, as the Roſe is not ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered from the Hauthorne, and as his Maieſty well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, if men be ſo carefull to haue their horſes and dogs of a good bréed, and race, which are onely for exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13521:10"/>
and ſuperficiall vſes and pleaſures, how much more ſhould they then wiues of their owne boſomes, from whom they expect to raiſe and continue their owne generations and poſterities vpon earth, to repreſent and preſerue aliue their owne image and virtues behind them, from generation to generation, <hi>vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad longuinqum, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. What yeares are moſt conuenient for mariage.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He forward Virgins of our age are of opi on, that this commodity can neuer be taken vp too ſoone, and therefore how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they neglect in other things, they are ſure to catch time by the fore-locke in this, if you aske them this queſtion, they will reſolue you fouretéene is the beſt time of their age, if thirteene bee not better then that, and they haue for the moſt the example of their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers before them, to confirme and approue their ability, and this withall they holde for a certaine ground, that be they neuer ſo little they are ſure thereby to become no leſſe; the effects that, for the moſt part, inſue thereafter, are dangerous births, diminution of ſtature, breuity of life, and ſuch like, yet all theſe paines will they aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for this pleaſure: Now as theſe will not ſtay till their youth, but marry in their childe-hood, before either bloud, or affection rypen them thereto by their earely forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo are their others that as much offend in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, by paſſing ouer their youth for certaine cautiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry worldly reſpects, to ſalute this ſociety with their age, like to him that hath ſuffered his houſe to burne downe to the bottome, before hee would ſéeke to extinguiſh the flame, when the other, as néedleſly forward, as he fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſlow, throwes on water ere any fire come néere it; the extremity in both is vtterly diſtaſtfull, and as I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13521:11"/>
ſhewed briefly the indiſcretion in either, ſo I might thus continue it further along in the firſt: that ſuch ſhould take vpon them to gouerne others that (which as may well appeare in this) know not yet how to gouerne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; the latter, that they vtterly abandon the right vſe of marriage, for if the chiefe end thereof be propagation and encreaſe, both for the Kingdome of earth and heauen, why then do they deferre ſo long till their bloud be froſty, and their bones be empty, their lamps bée waſted, and their ſpirits conſumed, hiding in the earth their talents from vſe, which might haue béene otherwiſe multiplyed by a lawfull vſury, to a happy encreaſe and excellent end, and therefore worthy ſuch of their iuſt reward, which is (for the moſt part) to periſh in themſelues as the laſt of their name and poſterity vpon earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diogenes</hi> being aſked what time of a mans life was beſt to marry, anſwered in youth it was too ſoone, and in age it was too late, cynically inſinuating thereby that it was beſt neuer: Indéed ſome of our infortunate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctions, might haue béene happy embracing his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, when Planets of maleuolent aſpect and influence are vnfortunately howſed, like two oppoſite poyſons in a ſtomacke, one euer ſicke of of another, fearefully porten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their owne deſtruction and ruine; yet not to diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort any that are to enter héerein, the beſt good and moſt abſolute perfection that euer was in the world, and moſt generall, neuer did all participate in the fruition thereof, although the greateſt number did; God gaue ſight to all, yet all pertake not the benefite thereof, health to all, yet ſome are daily incumbred with ſickneſſes, limbes to all, yet ſome wée ſée are decrepit and lame, although the moſt inioy them, theſe infirmities hauing in their being rather deficient then efficient cauſes, for God created not blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, lameneſſe, ſickeneſſe, or ſuch like, but the depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of their better oppoſites, is the cauſe of their producement and effect: So likewiſe in marriage,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13521:11"/>
God gaue a generall bleſſing to the firſt inſtitution and vſe thereof, Hée bleſt it by his Word, hée honoured it by his preſence, hée confirmed it by his miracles, where hée turned water into wine, to ſhew that thoſe that celebrate it in the right manner, to the lawfull and true end, ſhall haue their ſorrow turned into ioy, their water into wine; but the contrary, their ioy into ſorrow, that is, their wine into water.</p>
               <p>One ſaith, wiues are yong mens Miſtreſſes, compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for middle-age, and old mens Nurſes, ſo that a man may haue a quarrell to marry when hée will: But the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith héere, <hi>Reioyce in the wife of thy youth:</hi> As thereby hée would point out the fitteſt time; In thy youth whilſt thou haſt bloud in thy veines, &amp; marrow in thy bones, health in thy loynes, and ſecurity in thy ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, when thou maiſt beget an off-ſpring, and by courſe of time be ſo bleſt, as to ſée thy childrens children ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the Church, and Common-wealth, in honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Offices, and Functions, to thy peace of conſcience, and quietneſſe in thy laſt <hi>Dimittis:</hi> Late repentance, they ſay, is ſeldome true repentance; and it is obſeruable, that in theſe late marriages is ſeldome found that true comfort and happineſſe, which it is crowned withall in due ſeaſon, therefore beginne not the world, diuide not thy ſelfe, thy loue, when thou art going out of the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. That conueniency and fitneſſe in choyſe, is more to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, then either beauty, riches, or any other additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of minde or fortune.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this one, and abſolute greateſt action of a mans whole life, men, for the moſt part, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo careleſſe, in their will, or ſo blinded in their iudgement, or ſo carried away by affection, that they regard not that which moſt materially concerneth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13521:12"/>
the peace, the welfare, and felicity of their whole life and conſeruation therein; for their eye, for the moſt part, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ceizeth vpon beauty, and thoſe are ſuch that chooſe an Apple for the red ſide, as the ſerpent deceiued <hi>Eue,</hi> which afterwards in the taſte ſets the téeth on edge: or the heart vpon riches, and they are rather married to the ſubſtance then the owner: Some againe marry for gentility, not reſpecting their owne ignobility, and baſeneſſe, which for the moſt part, it vpbraideth them with all their life long; and though all of theſe are ioyned by the King (the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of Wedlocke) yet few vnderſtand the Morall thereof, which is a repreſentary fitneſſe to bée reſpected: I meane not equality or fitneſſe of ſtature, for the more equall coniunction and action, but a fitneſſe in affection, for as that being either too bigge, or too little, pincheth the finger or ſtayeth not on, ſo where this equality doth not ſympathie in affection there is either a falling off from the bond of this duty, or a ſhrinking vp of the ioy and felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty therein: The chollericke man, which for ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reſpect, maketh this his expected heauen a hell, by vnaptly conioyning vnto himſelfe prouocation and impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, euer to kindle that fire a freſh which of it ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes without further addition, the very peace, and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, life, and ſpirit, of ſoule and body, when as hée ſhould rather haue elected, as an allayer to this fury <hi>meekeneſſe,</hi> and <hi>indurance,</hi> ſuch alenitiues, as ſhould rather haue waſted the malady, then augmented the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; for what concord, or ſociety, can bee expected to bée inioyde, when natures, more repugnant then the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, are ioyned in one: frée ſpirits, with miſer diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, where they graple and tugge without eaſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſement, for breath and liberty: Heroycall thoughts with dull affections, where there is no correſpondence to there height or eleuation: Knowledge with ignorance, where there is no zeale to communicate; and age with youth, where there is no deſire of inioyment, preuenting
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13521:12"/>
the good by ſome blind inducement, which either might haue claimed by their likely-hood, in more ſutable fitneſſe, bearing the yoke with repining and diſpleaſure, as preſſing too heauily, which otherwiſe might haue béene ſupported with eaſe and delight, as ſcarce taſted or felt, Therefore (who euer thou art) know this in thy choyce, that wouldſt for bondage aduenture thy fréedome; that euery good woman, makes not for euery man a good wife, no otherwiſe then ſome one good diſh digeſteth with eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtomacke: therefore as for thy Trade thou wilt chooſe a fit ſeruant, for thy ſtomacke a fit diet, for thy body fit cloathing, ſo for thy inſeparable, daily, nightly ſociety, chooſe a fit companion, according to the Poets rule, in a leſſer ſence.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Elegat equalem prudens ſibi quiſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ſodalem.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let euery wiſe and diſcret man,</l>
                     <l>Choſe him a fit Companion.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>The Thiefe for his Burglaries takes his fitteſt opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity and ſociety: The Huſbandman his ſeaſons for his Séed time and Harueſt: The Lawyer the aduantage of Aſſizes and Termes, The Marchant for aduenture the Tide and the Winds, and all theſe the fitneſſe befriendeth the endeuour, and ſhall the huſband then thinke to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh his purpoſe, his peace, ſo great, and ſo greatly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on depending, without this vigilancy and obſeruance: The old rule will teach him new wit, in this aptneſſe, which ſaith:
<q>
                     <l>Hee that a fit wiſe to himſelfe doth wed,</l>
                     <l>In minde, birth, age, keepes long a quiet bed.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Art thou a remnant of the age of ſome miſpended youth, fallen from the badge of one baſeneſſe to another,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13521:13"/>
as frowned out of ſome conuenient Maiſters fauour, for not pleaſing thy Miſtreſſe, that now to ſupport thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wouldſt ſmoake thée out a liuing in ſome blind and conſcious corner, ſmell thée then a wife out a little tain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the ſwéeter for thy purpoſe, and as apt to fall downe as thy vapour to flie vp, taking care, (vnleſſe thou wilt diſranke thy ſelfe, or ſingle out from the too too common ſhame and abuſe in this kind) that ſhée bée ſuch a one as can take it, and being light can light it.</p>
               <p>Art thou a Marchant, a Marriner, a Termer, chooſe thée a wife of ſome Phlegmaticke humour, that like a rich Creditor, with her large ſtocke of vertue, without brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out, can forbeare thée, vpon occaſion, a month or two, a yeare or two, a Tearme, or voyage, leaſt other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thou abroad, ſhée prooue an Actor with thy Factor at home, or for thée, whilſt thou labours for this right in this caſe, do againſt thée that wrong in another, which no law can helpe, nor preuention hinder, nor patience beare; if otherwiſe, though thou eſcape the perils of the ſea, thou art in danger of the Pirates of the Land; or thou, though thou get a iudgement at the Hall, ſhalt be ſure to haue exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution againſt thée at home: And from whence elſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedes theſe lamentable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arres of houſholds, worſe then the open warres of Kingdomes, that deuoure and eate vp whole families: Whence procéeds theſe ſeparations, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, diſiunctions; whence ariſe they, but exhaled and drawne vp with the heate of this parabolicall ſunne, (the muck and mammon of the world) the beames where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of blinde the eye ſometimes of conſcience, as well of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and iudgement: whoſe conioyning of hands may reſemble the league betwéene the Low Countries &amp; Spaine, where hearts can no more bée brought to vnity and affection one another, then thoſe euer vowed enemies thus taken truce: Theſe reſpects I ſay, like that reſpect of ſtate, and no other, haue proſtituted, vnder one couering, many a froſty <hi>Ianuary,</hi> and youthfull <hi>May,</hi> many a <hi>greene
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13521:13"/>
deſire</hi> and <hi>gray performance,</hi> which could no more coha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite then theſe different ſeaſons, otherwiſe aforehand meant, and afterwards ſatiſfied, though with a ſhamefull breaking out, to the ruine and deſtruction of both the one, and the other; Meere Croanes, and many of my late re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, lip-bearded, as wiches, with their warted an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity and age, haue angled into their beds with this bayted golden hooke, (for luker of deſire and luſt) on their parties, youth whoſe chinnes haue neuer yet fallen vnder the razor, leſſe that way by their <hi>heate</hi> and <hi>haire,</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing man then their wiues, (wiues) nay rather Matrons, and Mothers, to their children proſtituted, the ſhame and vneuenneſſe whereof hath euen crackt this fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned wreath in the ring, broke <hi>Pryſcians</hi> head in the vnequall coniugations, the deſtruction whereof hath not ſlowly followed, but thus quickly, (like a <hi>Gangrene</hi>) crept on by a careleſſe neglect in the one, and earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in the other, and a timely repentance in both: The one thus (to his precedent aime) the better ſupported to his wilde pleaſures a broad, whilſt the other, with her fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated intention and hope, all tame and penitentiary, left deſtitute to bewaile her grieuance at home. But go fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, admit impoſſibilities, that <hi>Age</hi> and <hi>Youth, Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and <hi>Winter</hi> could bée one, yet how would the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumne</hi> with her tempeſts blaſt the <hi>Summer,</hi> and her tender buddes of that ſeaſon, and <hi>Summer,</hi> againe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting her contrary melting, her ſnowes and froſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to nothing, what panges and trauels, and throbbes, and throwes, would they ſuſtaine one with the other, till they brought an end and confuſion to both: euen ſo admit, that youth could aſſume ſuch a habite of grauity that might like an age, and age againe ſo ſhake off her vnneſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that ſhée could looke amiable in the freſh and greene eye of youth; yet muſt this mixture of vnequall heales bée more pernitious to either, then thoſe blaſting contrary ſeaſons one to another: From theſe vnequall coniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13521:14"/>
breake forth thoſe maiſterfull iealouſies, thoſe inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable diſcontents, that haue not ſet but euen in bloud and death, ruined their owners, afflicted and wrung in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to lamentations, their Friends, Allies, and Aſſociates, and drawne bloud from the heart of any one that had but a hand or finger in the carriage: Many inſtances of theſe we know of late times which we may remember, whilſt I ouerpaſſe them to recite one of more antiquity, as it is deliuered by Tradition.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Stowes Suruey.</note>An Aldermans wife, ſometimes of London, her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band deceaſed, and ſhée a rich widdow left, but as old in yeares, as rich in ſubſtance (more for deſire of portion then perſon) was ſolicited to an vnequall banes and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, by a yong and courtly Gentlemen (and which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ended her bane) whoſe deſire being obtained, and hée maiſter of her ſubſtance, moſt leudly lauiſhed it away vpon royotous and euill company, grew careleſſe of her regard, and vtterly abandoned her ſociety, both bed and boord, which when with ſorrow ſhée perceiued, with her too late repentance, her ſelfe thus rifled of her goods, vpbraided of her friends, forſaken of her huſband, deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of all comfort, ſhée tooke the euening to her mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, went into a Spring néere Shore ditch (a place that takes the name from a like fatall accident) and there ended her daies, and ſorrowes by drowning, which Fount to this day is chriſtned by her name, a remembrance of her miſery, and warning to aftertimes, and called (by her name) <hi>Dame Annis a Clere.</hi> And therefore who euer thou art, entering into this common garden of humanity, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for thy better bleſſing and proſperity therein, more then <hi>Beauty, Birth,</hi> or <hi>Riches,</hi> this <hi>Harmony</hi> and <hi>fitneſſe,</hi> wherein is no <hi>iarre,</hi> no <hi>ſtrife,</hi> no <hi>diſcontent,</hi> nor <hi>wearineſſe,</hi> and which ſhall land thée proſperouſly at the hauen of thy reſt, when this other, either <hi>tackling, fraught,</hi> or <hi>ſayle,</hi> may indanger to periſh thée in the floud.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13521:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. What is that chiefe moath, and canker, that eſpecially vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermineth and fretteth the marriage bed.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ride, Ambition, equality</hi> with others, the <hi>Example</hi> of others, <hi>variety</hi> of <hi>Appetite,</hi> the vnrealiſhneſſe of that which is lawfull, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of that which is reſtrained, is vnlawfull, and then the oratory of the diuell of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in the ſhape of an Angell of light, working vpon theſe aduantages hath ouerthrowne, and betrayed, to this vulture, and his mercileſſe talant, that fort and Cittadell, with as eaſy reſiſtencie as a Bower of glaſſe, that ſhould be ſo vnſpotted, but more impregnable then a Bulwarke of ſtone, admitted treaſon to the heart of the Citty, copt with the moſt dangerous enemy in the world, opened thoſe gates with weakeneſſe, and this ſtratageme, that an Engine ſhould not aſſayle with ſtrength, and might, broke downe the dore that ſtruck dead the owner, layed open thoſe incloſures, that haue bondaged the Lord of the ſoyle perpetually till death, to encloſe his owne ſuppoſed intereſt and vſe: <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>pride</hi> you twyn-borne ſiſters, you, you it is, and the dependancy of your eſtate (you true and indulcitate yſſues of <hi>Lucifer</hi>) that haue broken downe this hedge of the greateſt conſequence and ſite that euer was erected, and which elſe had kept out the aſſayling and ſeducing ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that batter and vndermine the very ſupportance, roote, and life-bloud of chaſtity it ſelfe, letting in at theſe caſements, euill conceits, and motiues more blaſting thereto, then the breath of lightning, made the vowes of marrriage of leſſe ſtability then the oathes of drunken men. <hi>Ambition, equality, example,</hi> you fore-mentioned euils, you foote-ball players which ſhort-héeled creatures it is you that are arraigned &amp; found guilty in this tryall.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:13521:15"/>The Countrey Damſell vnder the thacht roofe of her naturall habitation, where ſhe ſcarce euer thought of ſo much pride as handſomneſſe, neuer beheld her how other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe preſented then in a bowle of water, that dreamed more deuoutlier vnder that innocent couering being aſleepe, then others pray in their lofty Pallaces being awake, who can ſcarce there remember marriage but ſhee bluſhes to thinke what a ſhame it is to lye with a man: yet afterwards bring her to the Citty, enter her into that ſchoole of vanity, ſet but example before her eyes, ſhée ſhall in time become a new creature, and ſuch a ſtrong mutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall ſo ſtrangely poſſeſſe her, that ſhée ſhall haue new thoughts, new purpoſes, and reſolutions, and in the end ſo ſhoulder out her modeſty, that ſhée ſhall not bluſh to do that vnlawfully, which before ſhée was baſhfull to thinke on lawfully: Come to the Citty, there you ſhall haue ſome good amongſt many bad, but ſhould haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more were it not for this <hi>ſickeneſſe</hi> of this ill <hi>Example,</hi> therefore well were it with the world, <hi>If what were moſt done, were moſt good:</hi> Such a one could bée content (for any deſire of nouelty or change, or for any heate in her bloud, more then might bee lawfully allayed) to be honeſt, but that ſhee knowes ſuch a friend, and ſuch a Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man her Goſſip, haue their variety of Gownes, of giftes, of fauours, and variety of pleaſures to, interchanging with variety of perſons, and in this regard ſhée will bee no longer her owne foe, to kéepe her ſelfe longer without ſuch a friend, ſhée ſees the <hi>world takes notice of no more then it ſees,</hi> and <hi>they are accounted moſt chaſte, that can beſt ſeeme ſo:</hi> In this reſolution ſhée puls vp the <hi>Flood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates,</hi> where her tyde of vanity is ſwelled to the brimme, which immediately ore-flowes and drownes her therein, extinguiſhing all former ſparkes of vertue and reſpect, which before this conqueſt ſhée debated with, and beares her along with the periſhing multitude, for theſe brittle reſpects, that héere ſhée is inſnared with.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:13521:15"/>The Court, the very Element and Center of theſe ſinnes, the <hi>ne plus vltra,</hi> for any example beyond that, being the patterne to it ſelfe, and to others, the reſpects that ioyne there, are the reſpects of pleaſure, not of profite; the hygheſt ambition of theirs is to be moſt allured, moſt deſired, to haue moſt ſeruants, moſt friends, moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, and theſe ſhould preſage moſt falles, whoſe open out ſides boſomes, were their inſides ſo diſplayed, it would bée found a poore and idle ſinne had not there béene harboured, whoſe ſattin out-ſides, and ſilken inſides, ſoft rayment and ſwéete feeding, ſo ſtroake the ſkinne, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the bloud that it will not bee perſwaded.</p>
               <p>There is a Text in woman, that I would faine haue woman to expound, or man either; to what end is the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the embrodred haire, embared breaſts, virmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lioned chéekes, alluring lookes, faſhion gates, and Artfull countenances, effeminate, intangling, and inſnaring ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, their curles and purles of proclaiming petulan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, boulſtred, and layed out with ſuch example and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in theſe our daies, as with allowance and beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming conueniency, ſuch apiſh faſhions and follies, that the more ſeuerer out-worne ages of the world, deceaſed and gone, ſhould they haue but lifted vp their head and in their times would haue hyſſed out of countenance to death: But as to pleaſe, woman hath much ſtarched vp man from his ſlouenry, ſo to delight man (or rather his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my) hath the woman thus increaſed in prides, doth the world waxe barren through decreaſe of generations, and become like the earth, leſſe fruitfull then heeretofore: Doth the bloud looſe his heate, or the Sunne-beames become more watriſh and leſſe feruent then formerly they haue béene, that men ſhould be thus inflamed and perſwaded on to luſt: or hath this age of ſinne vſurped ſuch a ſéeming purity, or thought, that the moſt licenſed luſt, hath the originall from concupiſence or ſome taint of ſinne, and therefore muſt bée thus dragged vp to this anchor, like a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13521:16"/>
Pitcher by the eares, by theſe bloud neare-touching wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries, and inducements, no, rather the contrary witneſſe the ſuperfluity and increaſe of theſe our times, of this our Kingdome, that hath more people then paſture, more bringing forth then breeding, for that it is compelled to empty it ſelfe into farre diſtant Regions and Kingdomes: Is it not rather the contrary, when the youth of both ſexes are daily cropt in the bloſſome by this forward motion, or rather head-ſtrong deuill, and vnripely preſt to that action, foreſtalling maturity and fitneſſe, where a Veſtall ſhould bée more pointed at in a Cloyſter, then a Comet in the Aire: Is it not rather the contrary, when luſt is growne ſo vnbounded, ſo head-ſtrong, that it will not bee hemm'd nor incircled within any Lawes, or limites, of God, or man; when it will garbadge without all reſpect, or controule, vpon Adultery, fornication, poſſeſt, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſt, the bond, the free; where care ſhall more poſſeſſe a man to keepe his faire wife from foule play, when hee hath her, then iealouſy did to looſe her, when hee firſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ual'd for her; where vertue ſhall not ſo diſguiſe it ſelfe in any habite, but vice will trace it out and betray it. The ignorant Papiſts, or other ſectaries of Hereſies, moſt commonly giue no other reaſon for their ſeduced errors, then example of multitude, of parents, progenitors, or friends that went before them; ſo the example of this euill, ſo common, ſo much made of, ſo cockred, ſo thriuing, ſo bedecked, ſo admired, ſo dandled on the lap of Greatneſſe, of Authority, drawes millions to perdition after it, for the greateſt part neuer looke further then the example of the greateſt number; the Coach eaſily runnes that is drawne wtth many horſes, ſoone followes one where thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands leade the way: Theſe haue diſioyned in chambers by the deuill, that were conioyned in the Church by God, and yet it muſt be ingenuouſly confeſt, it is but <hi>a cold comfort, to goe to hote hell for company:</hi> Luſt, that boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling damned putrefaction of the bloud, that raging, ruling,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13521:16"/>
headſtrong ſinne of this age, that is too apt to breake out, though it went cloathed in <hi>Sacke-cloth,</hi> and <hi>Hairecloath,</hi> and fed onely (as ſaith an Authour) with the <hi>Capuchin</hi> dyet of graſſe and hearbes, and ſuch like, and ſuppreſt with all the ſubiection can be impoſed to ſubdue it, that yet like lime it would flaſh and flie out through out all theſe impoſitions: but on the contrary, we are ſo far from ſubduing that paſſion, and keeping it vnder, by any ſuch meanes, that it is attired and ſet out in the moſt Artfull bewitching, and inticing temptation that may be deuiſed, whole daies and nights, and thoughts and ſtudies, and coſts and cares, caſt away thereon, for the better ſucceſſe therein, though the worſe ill thereby, for the end thereof is but repentance and ſorrow.</p>
               <p>Another maine enemy, to open this breach, is impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of reſtraint and limitation, for that which is moſt forbidden is moſt deſired; Hee is the old deuill that ſtill tempts in that likeneſſe that came to <hi>Eue</hi> in Paradiſe, and perſwaded her to eate the forbidden fruite of the Tree of knowledge of good and euill, vpon whom he obtained ſuch a victory and conqueſt, in that firſt battell that euer was fought, that neuer ſince hath he diſtruſted the force of that ſtratageme: Euery woman is an abridgement of all woman-kind, containes the ſhape, the proportion, the lyniaments, the members, the vſe of all the women in the world, and likewiſe ſo of man; why ſhould not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire then, being ſo linked in the moſt ſufficient, and wiſeſt allowance, that God and man thought meete, couch and ſubmit it ſelfe to theſe ordinances, but that concupiſcence and luſt, inkindle deſire, and it findeth not delight in that it hath, but in that it would haue, according as the Poet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifyeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Luſt nere takes delight in what is due,</l>
                  <l>But ſtill leaues knowne delights to ſeeke out new.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13521:17"/>It lookes out of the window, where fuell is admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred where temptation entreth in: edgeth it ſelfe vpon one for reſpects that it can conceiue but not vtter; vpon an other, for ſome thing it likes, but knowes not what; It makes choyce of a third, for modeſty baites his luſt in that flame, to thinke with what lookes it could looke in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, that is ſo fiered with bluſhes in but proffered, concerning circumſtances, though farre diſtant and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from either time or action: Vpon a fourth, for her quaint conceite, and diſcouers by debating how ſhe could vſe it, being put to her <hi>non plus,</hi> in the bare point of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, with the beauty of a fift, to conceiue what a large fruition it were to be inflamed on the promontory of the Hill, when the demeanes, and adiacent Vallies, to that fuller ſurfet, reſtrained not their ſhades nor fountaines: And indeed, to conclude, there is none ſo ugly, none ſo deformed, but Luſt will finde argument to make vſe of it, may it but haue meanes to enioy it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. Aduice for choice, and whether it be beſt to marry a Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, or a Maide.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ee that marryeth a Widdow, hath but a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion in taile, and if ſhe proue good, may thanke death for his aime, if euill, vpbraide him, and not vniuſtly for his occaſion: He that takes her thus halfe-worne, makes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſhee hath that will pay for new dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſhee ſeemes to promiſe ſecurity in her peace, yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites many times to a troubleſome eſtate, when the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt atchieued ſcarce counteruailes the warres, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall of her loue is periſhed with the vſe, for what is once firmely ſet on, can neuer be cleanly taken off, and he muſt nere looke to bee enriched that way that hath her. The end of her <hi>Marriage</hi> is <hi>luſt</hi> and <hi>eaſe,</hi> more then <hi>affection</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:13521:17"/>
or <hi>loue,</hi> and deſerue what thou canſt, the dead ſhall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braide thee by the helpe of her tongue, flattered behind his backe, the more to vexe thee to thy face: The beſt is, though the worſe for thee, they are nauigable without difficulty, more paſſable then <hi>Virginia,</hi> and lye at an eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Rode, as vnſatiate as the ſea, or rather the graue, which many times y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſooner preſents them thether: At the deceaſe of their firſt huſbands, they learne commonly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trickes to turne ouer the ſecond or third, and they are in league with death, and coadiutors with him, for they can harden their owne hearts like iron to breake others that are but earth; and I like them the worſe that they will marry, diſlike them vtterly they marry ſo ſoone, for ſhee that ſo ſoone forgets the flower and Bride-groome of her youth, her firſt loue and prime of affection (which like a colour layed on in Oyle, or dyed in graine, ſhould cleaue faſt and weare long) will hardly thinke of a ſecond in the neglect and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of her age. Many preſidents wee haue againſt theſe ſuddaine, nay againſt theſe ſecond Marriages deriued from former times, the ages of more conſtancy, and ſhame of theſe latter. The daughter of <hi>M. Cato,</hi> beway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a long time the death of her huſband, being aſked which day ſhould haue her laſt teare, anſwered the day of her death (not the end of a month or yeare) for (ſaith ſhée) ſhould I méete with a good huſband, as I had before, I ſhould euer bée in feare to looſe him, if with a bad one, I were better be without him. In like manner, <hi>Portia,</hi> a yong and honourable Lady, hauing loſt her huſband, an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwered, ſolicited by another, <hi>A happy and chaſte Matrone neuer marries but once. Valeria,</hi> hauing loſt her huſband, importuned by another, anſwered; <hi>My husband euer liues in my thoughts. Arthemeſia,</hi> the wife of <hi>Mauſoll</hi> King of <hi>Corinth,</hi> could not not bée brought to any ſuch action, but ſtill anſwered, being mindefull of her huſband deceaſed, <hi>Vpon thy pillow ſhall neuer ſecond reſt his head;</hi> Shée dyed a widdow, and in memory of her huſband, ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13521:18"/>
that Monument, or Tombe, the coſt and fame where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hath ouerſpread the world: which Wife and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Lucinius</hi> thus further commendeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rex dudum erat, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There was a King, of whom it may be read</l>
                  <l>In ancient Stories, ſepulchred ere dead.</l>
                  <l>More wrong you'le ſay they did him, to depriue</l>
                  <l>Him of his Kingdome thus he being aliue.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>No he had all his rights, more then Kings haue</l>
                  <l>That rul'd a Kingdome, and raign'd in his graue.</l>
                  <l>A Kingdome, nay a little world and more,</l>
                  <l>A great world, and reſpected as before.</l>
                  <l>Nay, euen a Regiment that hath diſturb'd,</l>
                  <l>The ableſt health and pollicy to curb.</l>
                  <l>A womans heart and minde, and which more ſtrange</l>
                  <l>Free from variety of thought or change:</l>
                  <l>So willingly ſubiected to his bloud,</l>
                  <l>Ne're to depoſe him whilſt her Empire ſtood.</l>
                  <l>Of whom all loues and Lawes did firme remaine</l>
                  <l>In force, till one ſtone did encloſe them twaine.</l>
                  <l>Of whom it may be ſaid, now ſhee is gone,</l>
                  <l>Ther's few ſuch Toombes erected, women none.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Such a Widdow couldſt thou marry ſhée were worthy thy choyce, but ſuch a one ſhee could not bee, becauſe ſhee would not then marry.</p>
               <p>Compare the loyalty of our times with thoſe of more ancient, and ſée how they equall thy conſcience and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſe breaking, how with thy piled vp cheſtes, they build monuments of remembrances to thy name and memory after death; nay rather obſerue, but how their ambition, thus heated makes them forgetfull of themſelues as well as thee: Knowing this, who would not, with theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraughted times, to leaue the purchaſe of a Ladiſhip to his wife, glide like a ſhadow in his life vpon earth, with a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13521:18"/>
ſhrinking inſide, and penurious out-ſide, and ſléepe with broken thoughts and diſtracted dreames to gather with paine, and forbeare with want, that which his liuing ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my may afterwards ſpend with pleaſure and ſurfet with fulneſſe. Who can loue thoſe liuing that he knowes will ſo ſoone forget him being dead, that are but Summer Swallowes for the time of felicity, that will hang about ones necke as if they had neuer armes for others embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, or as though extreame affection without controule could not but this manifeſt it ſelfe and breake out; yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe, and ſuch a <hi>lethe</hi> of forgetfulneſſe ſhall ſo ſoone or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rake thée as if thou hadſt neuer beene, nay ſo little a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of time ſhall confine it, that ſhee ſhall not lie in her month but ſhée ſhall bée Churched againe, and open to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other all thy fruitions, with as freſh and plenteous an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite as the harlot to her next ſinner. Yonger brothers, and poore Knights, may ſometimes to theſe monſters make vſe of their byrths and Titles, making them pay déere (as it coſt) for their dubbing, and releaſe of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory they are in with old ranke and faſhion to their new <hi>Eliſeum,</hi> and inſtaulement; and it muſt be confeſt, vnwiſe they were, but with good boote and addition, to refuſe a Virginity to accept a Widdow-hood, and yet many times with a Turkiſh fate, wée pay déere for our <hi>Credo quod ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus,</hi> that article of Beliefe we too fondly build vpon, when wée pay for the iewell that another hath ſtollen, and in hope of treaſure imbrace y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ranſackt caſket, yet they are too blame that haue thus béene to blame, and for their ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy puniſhment their firſt night ſhall diſcouer them. Bee not ſuddaine therefore vpon thy reſolution in this point, becauſe deceite, many times, lurkes in a modeſt face, but let long acquaintance, or inquiry, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more ſecure thee. The Country deceiues the Citty, &amp; the Citty againe returnes it with intereſt, and luſt ſo raignes in both, that there is ſcarce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quantity of virgins to be found in either to match the Parable in the Scripture; they haue faces more fairer
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13521:19"/>
then men, but hearts more deformed then deuils: It is ill building vpon a broken foundation, amendment may ſkinne the ſoare, but the ſcarce will long after retaine a blemiſh, yet no doubt free thought, which is frée, and dreames and wiſhes, which are but ſhadowes, though the rilling ruffians that break through all boſomes, &amp; ſuperfici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally rauiſh all woman kinde, from eight to eighty, and no doubt from actuall tranſgreſſions many may be found frée, for there was neuer infection ſo generall but it ſpared ſome, neuer battell ſo great that all were wounded, ſome of <hi>Eues</hi> Off-ſpring haue withſtood the temptation, all haue not taſted the forbidden Trée; and ſuch a one if thou canſt pray, to prey vpon, ſhe hath portion enough without other portion if ſhée thus continue it, for ſhée ſhall make thee a father of vndoubted children, ſhee ſhall not wrinkle thy thoughts with diſtracting iealouſies, nor vpbraide with a former huſband thy vnkindneſſes; her Mayden thoughts ſhall receiue from thee a more perfect impreſſion of loue and duty, and returne it backe more legibly indor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and written, frée from all former character, inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or ſoyle; her affection ſhall be ſtrong, not allayed by former wearing, ſhee ſhall bée ſuch a one as it is a heauen to liue with all, a myſery to mourne without, ſhée ſhall bée to thy ſences and delight as the budding Roſe in the youth of the ſpring, nay ſhall be ſuch a one, that, <hi>Hee that walkes by thy dore ſhall point at her, and hee that dwels by her ſhall enuy him that hath her,</hi> and euery man ſhall admire his hap, but he moſt fully reioyce and be glad that hath her, and all generations ſhall call ſuch bleſſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:13521:19"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. Since the end of Marriage is iſſue, whether it be lawfull for old Couples to marry that are paſt hope of Children, or whether it be lawfull, for an old man to marry a yong Maide, or the contrary.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He chiefe end of Marriage is <hi>proles,</hi> Iſſue, yet there are other reſpects in that coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that no doubt may tollerate the moſt ancient in this kinde: God ſaw that it was not good for <hi>Adam</hi> to be alone therefore hée made him an helper, and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rather marry then burne,</hi> and as it is in another place; <hi>Vae ſolus: Woe to him that is alone, for if hee fall hee hath not one to helpe him vp:</hi> Now thoſe in age, to come nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to a common and ſub-correctiue vnderſtanding, are moſt defectiue in their members, and therefore moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to fall, and ſo by conſequence moſt need of this helpe to raiſe them vp, of this ſtaffe for their ſtay, and beſides for ought that euer I could heare, or obſerue, that age is moſt proue to ſcortch it ſelfe in the flames of that fire, and therefore may lawfully pertake the remedy againſt it, and for the latter propoſition, for ought I ſée, the Law forbids not the act, But the circumſtances may breed ſome dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, for if the wife be yong enough, though the huſband be nere ſo decrepit, ſhee ſhall not bee out of all likely-hood to ſée encreaſe of her body, but hee that thus vndertakes to mannage in his age, what hath ſhaked the heart of youth, may be commended for his valour, but ſhall nere be crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for his wiſedome; And for ſuch a one (I truſt) hee ſhall not need to bee iealous, for that his doubt ſhall bee apparantly enough reſolued. One asked <hi>Diogenes,</hi> vpon a time, for ſome direction how to chooſe a wife, becauſe hee was a Phyloſopher, ſaith he vnto him, fellow, chooſe one without a head (if thou canſt) without a body, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13521:20"/>
lims, ſo her hands ſhall not offend in ſtriking, nor her tongue in rayling, nor her body in luſting: Another time ſeeing a man in his olde age going to Church, to make vp his ſecond Marriage, ſaid; <hi>O foole, haſt thou ſo lately beene ſhipwracked, and wilt needs to ſea againe.</hi> The Law of God, nor man, doth not forbid ſuch Marriages, but no pollicy in earth commends them; man &amp; wife ſhould be two in one: but can heate &amp; cold, youth &amp; age, be in one and not bee repugnant, hee that aduentures ſo for ſweete meates, ſhall finde them reliſhed with much bitter ſauce, they ſay the <hi>Oake</hi> would longer laſt, were it not for the intwyning and embracing <hi>Iuy,</hi> but in this caſe I entend the contrary, for the aged Oake here blaſteth the yonger, Iuy with the heate of youth, muſt againe renue, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Poet.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>No ſharper corſiue to our blooming yeares,</l>
                  <l>Then the cold badge of Winter blaſted heyres.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Many worldly reſpects may conioyne theſe Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, but this <hi>ſudor</hi> will cracke in the wearing, and he that ſo old ſeekes for a nurſe ſo yong, ſhall haue pappe with a Hatchet for his comfort.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. The difference betweene Loue and Luſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Vſt,</hi> the deſtroyer of <hi>Loue,</hi> the ſupplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and vnder-myner of chaſtity, the Spring-froſt of beauty, the tyrant of the night, the enemy of the day, the moſt potent match-maker in all Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages vnder thirty, and the chiefe breaker of all from eighteene to eight, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts that in a hote bloud that it nere performes in a cold, a regarder onely of the preſent, and to that effect will with
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13521:20"/>
                  <hi>Eſau</hi> ſell a birthright for a meſſe of pottage, no longer eſteeming the obiect then the vſe, which in like example is thus further followed, according to a more common ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruance.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Friends, Souldiers, Women, in their prime</l>
                  <l>Are like to Dogges in Hunting time:</l>
                  <l>Occaſion, Warres, and Beauty gone,</l>
                  <l>Friends, Souldiers, VVomen, there are none.</l>
               </q>
               <p>More dangerous, when it roues without lymites, then the Lyon without the verge of his grate; for he but onely would depriue the body of life, but this both of life and ſoule, and fame, ſubiect to more oppoſite immediate paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and contradictions in it ſelfe then any ſence or humour in the nature of man: as now well entreated, fairely ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, lodged where it beſt likes, anon hated without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during, curſt ont of charity, thruſt out of dores, and yet not onely though all this more immediately oppoſite, then prepoſterouſly fondly headlong, that for a minutes ioy, will incurre a months ſorrow, that for one drop of water will mud the whole fountaine that gaue it, for one ſweete fruite will blaſt the whole Tree that bare it; whereas the effect and force of loue is contrary, opreſſing folly, ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing fury; aiming to preſerue, not to deſtroy, and to that end, regards the end, by ſubduing paſſions and motiues that would ſeeme to oppoſe the tranquility thereof, and in concluſion reioyceth in the true fruition without diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, without ſatiety, hauing captiuated and ſubdued, though with ſome difficulty, thoſe paſſions that ſence for a time would haue beene beſt pleaſed with, to tryumph at laſt in more full fruition to that purpoſe that one thus writeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:13521:21"/>
                  <l>Loue comforteth like ſunne-ſhine after raine,</l>
                  <l>But luſts effect is tempeſt after ſunne.</l>
                  <l>Loues golden ſpring doth euer freſh remaine,</l>
                  <l>Luſts winter comes ere ſummer halfe be done.</l>
               </q>
               <p>In <hi>Loue</hi> there is no <hi>enuy,</hi> no <hi>iealouſy,</hi> no <hi>diſcontent,</hi> no <hi>wearineſſe,</hi> for it digeſteth and maketh ſweete the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt labour, and of all things doth the neereſt reſemble the Diuine Nature, for <hi>God is Loue,</hi> it hath in it vnity without diuiſion, for true loue hath not many obiects, it is a <hi>fire much water cannot quench:</hi> Now <hi>Luſt</hi> contradicteth all theſe, for whereas <hi>Loue</hi> is bounded with eaſy lymites, <hi>Luſt</hi> is more ſpacious, hath <hi>no meane, no bound, but not to be at all,</hi> more deepe, more dangerous then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sea, &amp; leſſe reſtrayned, for the Sea hath bounds, but it hath none; not woman but all woman-kind is the range thereof, and all that whole ſect not able to quench it neither: Full of enuy it is, for it enuies all without his reach, and enuies it owne nature that it cannot be ſatisfied: walking for the moſt part in ſimilitude of an old Goate, in the ſhape of an incontinent man.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Loue</hi> there is no lacke, in <hi>Luſt</hi> there is the greateſt penury, for though it be cloyed with too much, it pines for want: Ambitious it is, for where it treades it puffes vp, and leaues a ſwelling after it, turnes low flattes into little Mountaines downe, which precipitate folly tumbles headlong to confuſion, a haſty breeder of diſinheritable ſinners it is, ſuch as haue more pleaſure in the begetting, then comfort in the bringing forth, beſt contented when it looſeth moſt labour. To conclude, though Loue and Luſt in a halfe brother-hood, dwell both vnder one roofe, yet ſo oppoſite they are that the one, moſt commonly, burnes downe the houſe that the other would build vp.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:13521:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. The beſt way to continue a woman chaſte.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S not the <hi>Magitians Ring,</hi> nor the <hi>Italians Locke,</hi> nor a continuall <hi>Iealouſy</hi> euer watching ouer her, nor to humour her will in idle fancies, adorne her with new fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, (as the well appayed folly of the world in this kinde can witneſſe) but for him that would not be baſely madde with the multitude, would not beſpeake folly to Crowne him, would not ſet that to ſale that hee would not haue ſold, for who ſets out his ware to be cheapned and not bought, that would not for his <hi>Shop</hi> haue his <hi>Wife, for a relatiue ſigne</hi>) is to adorne her decently, not dotingly; thriftily, not laciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly; to loue her ſeriouſly, not ceremoniouſly; to walke before her in good example (for otherwiſe how canſt thou require that of thy wife that thou art not, wilt not be thy ſelfe, <hi>Vis tu vxorem tuam victricem eſſe &amp; tu victus ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:</hi> Wouldſt thou expect thy wife a conquerour when thou thy ſelfe lieſt foyled at the ſame weapon) to acquaint her with, and place about her good and chaſte ſociety, to buſy and apply her mind and body, in ſome domeſticke, conuenient, and profitable exerciſes, according to her education and calling, for example to the frailty of that whole ſexe, hath a powerfull hand, as it ſhall induce either to good or euill.</p>
               <p>There are of opinion that there is in Marriage an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euitable deſteny, not to be auoyded which is either to be <hi>Acteon'd,</hi> or not to bee, if it bee not, as is the opinion of ſome damned in the errour of <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> then let him take a houſe in <hi>Fleete-ſtreete,</hi> diuide it like an Inne, into as many ſeuerall lodgings as roomes, make his wife Chamberlaine to them all, attire her like a ſacrifice, paint her out like a <hi>Mayors</hi> poſts, or May-poole, let her haue
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13521:22"/>
freſh youth and high féeding, luſtfull company to incite her, her huſband abſent: all theſe opportunities preſent, yet notwithſtanding this deſteny ſhall preſerue him, to weare his brow as ſleeke, as hée that neare fetched againe the loſt ribbe to his ſide, as vnbunched as the front of a Batchelour; But if the contrary, bee ſhee the moſt pure in ſeeming, a very ſiſter of that Sect, the opinion of the <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>owniſts</hi> ſhall ſo neere cleaue to her ſkinne, that ſhée ſhall beſate thy forehead in thy <hi>ſleepe,</hi> kill thee <hi>dead</hi> in that image of thy <hi>graue;</hi> Bee ſhee <hi>Papiſt,</hi> abſolution ſhall ſo reſolue her, that ſhee ſhall ſinne vpon preſumption, nay though thou hadſt <hi>Argus</hi> eyes thou ſhalt not eſcape it, for
<q>
                     <l>No pollicy, they ſay, can that preuent,</l>
                     <l>Whereto two parties giue their full conſent.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Bee ſhee what ſhee will in this caſe, it ſhall bee all one for thee to reſtraine or to giue liberty, where thou dwelleſt or what thou doeſt, for thy deſteny is ſo allotted and it ſhall be accompliſhed: The raſh opinion, and careleſſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of either is worthy the reward, which for the moſt part, it doth deſeruedly receiue.</p>
               <p>It was an errour in Religion that one <hi>Ludouicus</hi> had, who had giuen himſelfe ouer to this damnable opinion and ſecurity of the deuill, that if he were ordained to bee ſaued, ſaued hee ſhould bee without any enquiry or dilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of his; if otherwiſe, though hee toyled to death in his beſt endeuour, it would not helpe nor reſerue him; In this conceite, ſetling himſelfe in the moſt Epicurian and diſolute courſe of liuing that might bee, hee continued, till vpon a time hee fell into a moſt grieuous extremity of ſickeneſſe, when ſending for a <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> who before hand acquainted with his damnable errour, came not, but ſent him word that hee needed not his helpe, for if his houre were come he could not preſerue him, if otherwiſe, hee ſhould recouer though neuer any thing were admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13521:22"/>
vnto him; by which eaſy application hee vnderſtood himſelfe, and that he muſt vſe the beſt meanes and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, as well for the ſafety of his ſoule, as the preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his body, not knowing the euent of their concealed ends, and ſo at once (by that meanes) was happily cured both in minde and body.</p>
               <p>In no leſſe palpable errour are thoſe, that ſo wittingly and violently, are carried on either ſide in this dangerous ſtreame of a corrupted iudgement to the apparanteſt ſpectacle and certainteſt ſhame that woman may do them, making that vnqueſtionable their diſhonour by this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, which a ſober courſe might haue directed to a more certaine end, Therefore who euer thou art that wouldſt not winke at ſuch a ſhame, that ſo profite doth ſuccéed, wouldſt not regard whether hand brought it in, vſe a good indeuour, ſuch foreſight and warineſſe as may prouide for <hi>competency,</hi> preuent <hi>indigence</hi> and <hi>want</hi> two great allayers of affection, and a maine inciter of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient bearers to this folly and abuſe, and aboue all ſéek to <hi>plant in her Religion,</hi> for ſo ſhee cannot <hi>loue God but withall ſhee muſt honour thee,</hi> increaſe her knowledge in good things, and giue her certaine aſſurance and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of thy loue, that ſhe may with hers againe the more reciprocally equall thy affection; <hi>For true loue hath no power to thinke, much leſſe act amiſſe:</hi> And theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetely put in practiſe ſhall more preſerue at all times, and temptations, then <hi>Spies,</hi> or <hi>Eyes, Iealouſie</hi> or any <hi>reſtraint,</hi> for theſe ſometimes may bee deluded, or ouer watched, or preuented by oportunity, but this neuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:13521:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> The patterne of a bad huſband, and a good wife, in two Letters inſtanced.</head>
               <lg>
                  <head>1 LETTER.</head>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>AIRE Miſtreſſe, what ſo long I haue expected,</l>
                  <l>And till this oportunity neglected,</l>
                  <l>Is now ſo happened as it would inuite</l>
                  <l>Mee to enioy my abſolute delight.</l>
                  <l>Your huſband abſent, and your ſeruants gone,</l>
                  <l>And you, but with your Maide, left all alone.</l>
                  <l>Where leaſt ſad Care, or Melancholy grieue you,</l>
                  <l>My beſt endeuour's ready to releiue you.</l>
                  <l>What Female Comfort can one woman finde,</l>
                  <l>Within the bed with other woman-kinde?</l>
                  <l>What tedious gate the yrkſome howers do keepe,</l>
                  <l>When there's no ioy to wake, no minde to ſleepe?</l>
                  <l>Beſides, the fearefull terrours of the night,</l>
                  <l>Which women and weake minds do much affright:</l>
                  <l>All which, faire loue, if you'le be rul'd by mee,</l>
                  <l>Wee will conuert ſo farre from what they bee</l>
                  <l>That thoſe which now are bitter for to thinke,</l>
                  <l>Shall taſte like <hi>Nectar</hi> that the Gods do drinke.</l>
                  <l>The ſtrangeſt Monſter that was euer bred,</l>
                  <l>That Seas haue nouriſht or elſe Deſart fed,</l>
                  <l>Tranſported from his ſolitary den,</l>
                  <l>A common obiect to the ſight of men,</l>
                  <l>Looſeth his admiration and delight,</l>
                  <l>In little time, and pleaſeth not our ſight:</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Appetite,</hi> the <hi>Viand</hi> nere ſo good,</l>
                  <l>Cloyd with one <hi>Diſh</hi> will ſoone diſtaſt her <hi>Food;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That <hi>Muſick</hi> of all other beſt wee deeme,</l>
                  <l>If euer in one <hi>Key</hi> we harſh eſteeme:</l>
                  <l>Mans nature doth deſire to heare and try</l>
                  <l>Thinges that are new, to taſt variety;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:13521:23"/>And I of <hi>Woemen</hi> this opinion hold,</l>
                  <l>They are not much in loue with things are old,</l>
                  <l>Which makes mee thus more boldly to diſcouer</l>
                  <l>My ſelfe vnto you, your new friend and louer:</l>
                  <l>In hope to be accepted, for whoſe pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>I'le ſpend my beſt life, and my deereſt treaſure.</l>
                  <l>Obiect not you already are inioy'd,</l>
                  <l>VVith <hi>Venus</hi> pleaſures dul'd and ouercloid.</l>
                  <l>VVhy ioyfull <hi>Widdowes</hi> when their huſbands die</l>
                  <l>Might this obiect, but yet you ſee they try;</l>
                  <l>Becauſe they thinke variety of men,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>May make old pleaſures new delights agen.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shee that contents her ſelfe with any one,</l>
                  <l>For many nights as well might lie alone.</l>
                  <l>Leſſe difference is not twixt the virgine life,</l>
                  <l>And ſtate of pleaſure, being cald to wife</l>
                  <l>Then is betweene the <hi>Elizeum</hi> of one <hi>Bed,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That croſly fated, to that's largely-ſped.</l>
                  <l>I haue a wife my ſelfe, I tell you true,</l>
                  <l>Yet in the old kind ſeeke for pleaſures new:</l>
                  <l>Taking not now delight that I haue tooke,</l>
                  <l>To ſhake the Tree that I ſo oft haue ſhooke.</l>
                  <l>VVee ſee in any Country that we dwell,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Aire</hi> the <hi>Earth,</hi> nay <hi>All</hi> that others tell:</l>
                  <l>Yet notwithſtanding 'tis our commonſt faſhions,</l>
                  <l>To ſeeke out other Kingdomes other Nations.</l>
                  <l>Each woman doth abridge all woman-kinde,</l>
                  <l>But yet one woman fits not each mans minde:</l>
                  <l>Nor euery man, experience too too common,</l>
                  <l>Can fit, can pleaſe, or ſatisfie each woman.</l>
                  <l>Since then the Sence, the Appetite and minde,</l>
                  <l>In freſh variety all pleaſure finde;</l>
                  <l>Let vs then meete all nice reſpects to ſmother,</l>
                  <l>And fully ſatisfie and ioy each other:</l>
                  <l>So ſhall I reſt by your obligement due,</l>
                  <l>A ſecret friend and faithfull ſeruant true.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:13521:24"/>The world can iudge no further then it ſpies,</l>
                  <l>And where we act ſhall be from ſight of eyes,</l>
                  <l>Windowes nor wals, can neither heare nor ſee,</l>
                  <l>And for the bed 'tis tride for ſecreſy:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then ſeeme but chaſte, which is the chiefest part,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For what wee ſeeme each ſees, none knowes the heart.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſo your huſband, and the world will deeme,</l>
                  <l>You to be that you are not, but do ſeeme.</l>
                  <l>Your huſband hee's abroad, where I'me affray'd</l>
                  <l>He hath deſerued to be ſo appay'd.</l>
                  <l>My Chaine heere take you, weare it for my ſake,</l>
                  <l>And as you finde me yours account ſo make.</l>
                  <l>And here's my Ring in earneſt of a friend,</l>
                  <l>The lateſt Token that my Wife did ſend.</l>
                  <l>And here's my Purſe, within it ſtore of Gold,</l>
                  <l>Able to batter downe the ſtrongeſt Hold:</l>
                  <l>Your dainty lymbes ſhall be more neatly clad,</l>
                  <l>In coſtlier Rayment then they erſt haue had:</l>
                  <l>And for your ſtomacke it ſhall not diſgeſt</l>
                  <l>Any thing, but the rareſt, and the beſt.</l>
                  <l>Theſe daily from me with a pleaſing cheare,</l>
                  <l>Which husbands grutch to part with once a yeare.</l>
                  <l>Though for their maintenance I ſell my land,</l>
                  <l>Diſherite heyres for that I will not ſtand:</l>
                  <l>So you be mine in that ſence I conceiue you,</l>
                  <l>Which till your anſwere manifeſt, I leaue you.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>HER REPLY.</head>
                  <l>ABuſed ſir, much grieu'd am I to ſee,</l>
                  <l>That you ſo long haue tarried Time and Mee,</l>
                  <l>And now when both your good ſeeme to conſpire,</l>
                  <l>They ſhould in no ſort anſwere your deſire:</l>
                  <l>My huſbands abſence ſeemeth to import</l>
                  <l>In your conceite ſome hope to ſcale his fort;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:13521:24"/>But know by that you ſmall aduantage finde,</l>
                  <l>For he is alwaies preſent in my minde:</l>
                  <l>The thought of whom, what ere his perſon bee,</l>
                  <l>Is able to repulſe your battery.</l>
                  <l>And for the howres that you ſo tedious deeme,</l>
                  <l>That by your preſence would ſo ſhortned ſeeme:</l>
                  <l>I cannot tell with others what 't might do,</l>
                  <l>With me 'twould rather make one houre ſeeme two:</l>
                  <l>And for the fearefull terrours of the night,</l>
                  <l>What could affright me worſe then would your ſight.</l>
                  <l>My Maid and I, a pleaſure not repented,</l>
                  <l>Will tell old Stories long ago euented</l>
                  <l>To paſſe the time, or when ſuch watch we keepe,</l>
                  <l>Wee'le thinke good thoughts, or pray vntill we ſleepe:</l>
                  <l>For know my vntainted minde did euer hate,</l>
                  <l>To buy damnation at ſo deere a rate:</l>
                  <l>To taſt ſweete <hi>Nectar</hi> for a day or howre,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And euer after to digeſt the ſowre.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Tis not variety I ſeeke or craue,</l>
                  <l>My whole delight is in the one I haue:</l>
                  <l>And ſhe that's not contented with her lot,</l>
                  <l>I hold more monſter then the Sea hath got.</l>
                  <l>The friendſhip which you proffer me preſerue,</l>
                  <l>For thoſe that will your kindneſſe more deſerue.</l>
                  <l>The obiection here you alledge is fondly ſtrange,</l>
                  <l>That woemen, though old cloathes they loue to change</l>
                  <l>And fancies to in ſomething, doth't inferre</l>
                  <l>That in this groſſe point they muſt therefore erre.</l>
                  <l>I am anothers parcell I confeſſe,</l>
                  <l>And you by your acknowledgement no leſſe,</l>
                  <l>Now what a ſinne were this vnworthy life,</l>
                  <l>I ſo to wrong my huſband, you your wife:</l>
                  <l>My huſband that dare ſweare that I am iuſt,</l>
                  <l>Should I ſo much deceiue his honeſt truſt?</l>
                  <l>Your wife, although a party I not know,</l>
                  <l>I hope imagines likewiſe of you ſo.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:13521:25"/>For ſhame go then repent and be not naught,</l>
                  <l>Be worth her good opinion, honeſt thought.</l>
                  <l>Let fleſhly widdowes when their huſbands die</l>
                  <l>They nere did loue, ſeeke new variety:</l>
                  <l>For me I vow, if death depriue my bed,</l>
                  <l>I neuer after will to Church be led</l>
                  <l>A ſecond Bride, nor neuer that thought haue,</l>
                  <l>To adde more weight vnto my huſbands graue,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In ſecond huſband let mee bee accurſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>None weds the ſecond, but who kils the firſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>You haue a wife you write, giue her your loue,</l>
                  <l>And that will all your wandring thoughts remoue;</l>
                  <l>You loue her not, by theſe effects I ſee,</l>
                  <l>For where loue is there's no ſatiety.</l>
                  <l>Can you ſo farre forget humanity,</l>
                  <l>As hauing ſhak't the fruite diſpiſe the Tree:</l>
                  <l>It is not loue but luſt, that thus abuſes,</l>
                  <l>To make it weary of the walkes it vſes.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Coelum non Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, &amp;c.</note>Thoſe that to forraine Countries do repaire,</l>
                  <l>Change not their minds, although they change the Aire,</l>
                  <l>Preferring ſtill, through nouelty deſire,</l>
                  <l>Their Countries ſmoake, before anothers fire.</l>
                  <l>Like vſe obſerue vnto your ſelfe to take</l>
                  <l>From the obiection that you ſeeme to make:</l>
                  <l>That though you ſee of beauteous women many,</l>
                  <l>And you by choyce poſſeſſe the mean'ſt of any,</l>
                  <l>More to reſpect her you your wife haue made,</l>
                  <l>Then others ſunſhine, to your proper ſhade.</l>
                  <l>Suppreſſe that luſt, that ſoule and body wounds,</l>
                  <l>For where it once breakes ore, it hath no bounds,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One woman doth abridge all womankind,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The volume then at large why would you finde:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For ſure I thinke where that doth beare no prize</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Booke at large might weary, not ſuffice.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>An other Argument to backe your ſute,</l>
                  <l>You alledge that walles and windowes will be mute,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:13521:25"/>And that the world hath no ſuch peircing eie,</l>
                  <l>The ſecret of the darke to ſearch and trie:</l>
                  <l>As if there were not one, whoſe power impartes,</l>
                  <l>To ſee through Dores, &amp; Windowes, &amp; through Hearts,</l>
                  <l>From whoſe bright eye, no ſecreſy can hide,</l>
                  <l>That which is guilty and would not be ſpide,</l>
                  <l>Then what auailes to haue the world aquite vs,</l>
                  <l>When our Conſcience like a fiend ſhall fright vs.</l>
                  <l>And for the Bed although it cannot tell,</l>
                  <l>Yet out their ſhame will breake that do not well.</l>
                  <l>My huſband he's from home I muſt confeſſe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe actes you meaſure by your guiltineſſe,</l>
                  <l>But where ſo ere he be, well may he ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>Ere any ſuch thought from my heart proceed:</l>
                  <l>Admit hee were in euill ſo compact</l>
                  <l>Would I reuenge the wrong by ſuch an act,</l>
                  <l>If that I ſhould, were't not a helpeleſſe part,</l>
                  <l>To kill my ſoule becauſe he brake my heart.</l>
                  <l>Your Chaine of Gold here backe againe I ſend,</l>
                  <l>Il'e no Earneſt ſure of ſuch a Friend:</l>
                  <l>And there's your Ring, full little doth ſhe know</l>
                  <l>That ſent in loue, that you would vſe it ſo:</l>
                  <l>And there's your Purſe, and all the Gold therein,</l>
                  <l>The're <hi>Wicked Angels</hi> that would tempt to ſin.</l>
                  <l>My Fort is more impregnable then they.</l>
                  <l>That much perſwade, although they little ſay.</l>
                  <l>As for my bodies homely cloathing weed,</l>
                  <l>It keepes me warme, ſufficeth natures need,</l>
                  <l>Which ſcarce more coſtlier do, and for my fare,</l>
                  <l>My diſhes wholeſome, though they homely are.</l>
                  <l>Let thoſe that diſcontented do abide,</l>
                  <l>Go wrong their huſbands to maintaine their pride,</l>
                  <l>For me the meaneſt ragge would hide my skinne,</l>
                  <l>Should better pleaſe me, then rich roabes of ſinne,</l>
                  <l>Which when I aske, my reaſon ſhall be ſuch,</l>
                  <l>No huſband in the world ſhall need to grutch.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:13521:26"/>Then for your heyres, reſerue your lands vnto them,</l>
                  <l>They ſhall not curſe my bones that did vndo them.</l>
                  <l>Call backe your ſelfe and thinke I am your friend,</l>
                  <l>That thus would ſtay you from your wilfull end:</l>
                  <l>Call backe your ſelfe, or I may ſafety tell</l>
                  <l>You are running downe the ſteepeſt hill to hell;</l>
                  <l>As when cold bloud, and better thoughts ſhall ſhew,</l>
                  <l>You'le hold then your friend, though now your foe:</l>
                  <l>And more reioyce in that I did refell,</l>
                  <l>Your lawleſſe pleaſure, then conſent: Fare-well.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> An admonition to Huſbands and Wiues for vnity and concord.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N that you are bound, you muſt obey, for this knot can neither bee cut nor vnlooſed, but by death, therefore as wiſe priſoners incloſed in narrow roomes ſute their mindes to their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, and not impatient they can go no further, aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their paine by knocking their heads againſt the walles, ſo ſhould it bee the wiſedome both of Huſbands and Wiues, that haue vndergone either this curſe, or bleſſing, as the ſucceſſe or vſe may make it vnto them, to beare it with patience and content the aſſwager of all maladies, and miſfortunes, and not to ſtorme againſt that which will but the deeper plunge them in their owne miſery: For what madneſſe were it for any one to croſſe himſelfe daily, becauſe another hath croſſed him once? or becauſe another hath vexed him, therefore to vexe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? Who is ſo weake in diſcretion, that by ſome diſaſter hauing blemiſhed one eye, for griefe thereof, will weepe out the other. That mother tries a mercileſſe concluſion:
<q>
                     <pb n="05" facs="tcp:13521:26"/>
                     <l>Who hauing two ſweet Babes, when death takes one,</l>
                     <l>Will ſlay the other, and be nurſe to none.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore ſéeing it is ſo, whoſoeuer thou art in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſter, ſéeke to plant an affection and loue, at leaſt wiſe a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to that which muſt of neceſſity bee endured: for there is nothing ſo eaſie that the want of this may not make hard: nor nothing ſo harſh that this may not better temper: there are many occaſions that this age admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth more then former haue done of the vſe of this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, (though all other ruſt by the walles of peace) intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the ouer-curious reſpects of ſecondary cauſes by ſecndary perſons, that for theſe vſes periſh the principall, by ioyning hands where hearts are more diſ-iunctiue then different ſectaries: and what is the iſſue of this but a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry patience, or ſudden deſtruction. Others conioyne them ſelues by vntimely folly, and theſe many times haue a timely repentance when pleaſures ebbe, and ſorrowes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to flow. As for inſtance, a youth of able meanes, hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full expectation, equall carriage, regardfully befriended, carefully watched ouer, purpoſed to better deſtiny, pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked on by ſome rebellious bloud, and guilty oportunity, ſtrikes downe all theſe hopes in the heat of his luſt, with a greaſy Kitchin-weneh in a corner, ceizeth her to his proper vſe for vnlucky conſequences, this being done, oppreſſed in minde, forſaken of his friends, ſhall hee the more augment his miſery, by thought of this his peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted felicity, with rage, and euill ſuffring, no rather let him loue her, ſince it was his fortune to haue her, and his fault to take her, and indeuour ſo to worke and huſband that croſſe beginning, to a more happy continuance and ending, taking S. <hi>Paules</hi> counſell to his practiſe, which thus aduiſeth, <hi>Huſbands loue your wiues, and be not bitter vnto them:</hi> Loue them for your owne peace, for your owne profite, dwell with them according to your
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13521:27"/>
wiſedomes as with the weaker veſſels, for there is no offence where loue is, for loue couereth the multitude of offences, of diſlikes, and becauſe the rather that God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted it, who Himſelfe is Loue; ſetting aſide contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, domeſticke ciuill, vnciuill ſtrife, the forerunner of ruine and the Purgatory vpon earth; remembring who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they be that fall into this predicament, they haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and man by ioyning of hands, taken an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting peace one of another, more inuiolably to be kept then the leagues of Nations; for as nothing is more odious in the ſight of God or man, then ſelfe violence againſt a mans owne perſon, and there was neuer any inraged that way but wanted either reaſon or faith in the deepeſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content; ſo then by this conſequence hee muſt either bee mad or deſperate, that ſhall to that end lay hands on his wife, being pact of himſelfe, for they are no more two but one, as <hi>Adam</hi> and his Rib at firſt were but one ſide till ſeuered and diuided from him, ſo after by marriage it was conioyned againe to as abſolute vnity as before, after which hee pronounceth and thus witneſſeth of himſelfe: <hi>She is fleſh of my fleſh, and bone of my bone,</hi> he the head, and ſhe as part of the members, which ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to be diuided and at oddes, were as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hand to lift vp, or the foot to kicke againſt the head, the King and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor, or the head againſt theſe his inſtruments, ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and miniſters, the harmony whereof in this little world of man, may inſtruct in example all houſhold Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths in the world, to vnity. Common-wealthes I ſay: for euery married man, for the moſt part, hath thrée Common-wealthes vnder him: hee is a Huſband of a Wife, a Father of Children, and a Maiſter of Seruants, and therefore had néede of gouernment in himſelfe that muſt gouerne all theſe, and to that purpoſe cannot take vnto himſelfe a better practiſe or preſident, then from this vniformity of the body, where the head ſtands aloft like a King in his Three, giuing direction and command to all
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13521:27"/>
his Subiects, biddeth the foote goe, and it goeth, the hand fight and it fighteth, the members aſſiſt and they aſſiſt it, and this harmony preſerues the whole man, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe would deſtroy it, ſo muſt it betweene man and wife that Myſticall head and member or both periſh, and for that reaſon, ſhall a <hi>man forſake father and mother</hi> (the neereſt that elſe could bee) <hi>and cleaue to his wife, being then no more two but one;</hi> and which hee taketh from her parents and friends not to offer her violence, but to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that loue with increaſe which for his ſake in theſe ſhee parteth with, and ſhee likewiſe to him, which beſides the profite, hath the applauſe both of God and man, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the alluſion of the <hi>Pſalme 133. Ecce quam bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num &amp; iucundum fratres habitare in vnum:</hi> Therefore auoide Diſcord thou that wouldſt ſee the fruite of thy labours, for vnity gathereth what diſcord diſpearſeth; auoide Iealouſy that vnreſolued vexation, that labours to ſeeke out what it hopes it ſhall not finde, that many times forrunnes that euill which it cauſeth to follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, being the author of diſſention, diſtaſt, miſery, and ſometimes of murder too, as many examples teſtify, of which I haue here inſerted one of moſt ancient truth and lamentable action, of a King that had a ſonne by whoſe ſword it was prophecyed his owne father and mother ſhould periſh, who therefore to preuent that fatall deſteny forſooke his inheritance and went into a farre diſtant Country to inhabite, where fortune yet fauouring hee increaſed to great honour and riches, and to augment his greater felicity, was eſpouſed to a wiſe right noble, rich, and exceeding beautifull, of whoſe welfare and happy ſucceſſe his father and mother afterwards hearing (being depoſed of their kingdome, and in extreame miſery) tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled to viſite for reliefe and ſuccour, and happening to his houſe in his abſence, where making themſelues knowne vnto his wife to bee her huſbands father and mother, ſhe kindly entertained them, &amp; when hauing well
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13521:28"/>
repleniſhed their bodies by food and ſuſtenance, to reſt them the eaſier after their trauell, ſhee laid them both in her huſbands bed; after which hee ſuddenly entring in poſſeſſed with this deadly iealouſy, and miſſing his wife goes into the chamber, where perceiuing two in his bed a ſleepe, hee ſo inraged with paſſion (taking it to bee his wife and ſome adulterer with her) drew forth his ſword and ſlew them both thereon at once, which when hee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued his father and mother, hee heauily repented with ſorrow and woe, and ſhortly after dyed with griefe and penſiueneſſe. And beſides all this becauſe it is thought (for the moſt part) to call a mans owne guiltineſſe into queſtion, as <hi>Petrarch</hi> to that purpoſe well obſerueth, who thus noteth:
<q>
                     <l>There's no man iealous I durſt paſſe my word,</l>
                     <l>Nor feares the ſcabberd but hath ſtrooke with t'ſword.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>If children, which are the very pledges of loue, make you parents, reliſh their tender yeares with learning and piety, let Gods Law bee the ſeaſoning of their firſt thoughts, for wee know by experience, greene veſſels long reliſh of the firſt liquour they receiue, and by inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction they may bee as ſoone taught to ſay <hi>Hoſanna</hi> to <hi>CHRIST,</hi> as Bald-pate to <hi>Eliſha;</hi> aſſoone a good word as a bad ſcoffe: Affect not one more then another, loue them all, but dote vpon none, with the folly of the moſt; let them bee children not wantons, walke before them eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, their more riper yeares with the more obſeruant example, which will bee better to them then many good leſſons. Repine not with the wicked worldling, who had rather ſee his counting houſe inuironed with vpbrayding bagges then his Table with this bleſſed garland of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but bee thankefull for them, what euer thy pouerty, for as they are <hi>Pignora,</hi> Pledges, ſo are they <hi>Benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones,</hi> bleſſings; and it ſhall bee more pleaſing to thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13521:28"/>
vpon thy death-bed to ſeale them as treaſure for the Kingdome of heauen, to yeeld vp thy ſpirit in the midſt of their inuironing, then to vnſeale ſo many bagges of euill heaped treaſure to nere after performed Legacies, euery peece wherein ſhall rend thy heart in peeces at that houre, to thinke of the guilty atchieuing thereof: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides hee that hath much riches, is ſubiect to many cares, many feares, dread of oppreſſion of violence; but hee that hath many children hath euen a peace in warre, a ſecurity euen in greateſt danger, for hee ſhall ſpeake boldly with his enemies in the gate, they are as ſo many ſwords in thy defence, ſo many arrowes in thy Quiuer, Arrowes (as ſaith one) becauſe they may bee ſo leuelled by good education and example, to ſhoote at thine enemies, as by the contrary againſt thy ſelfe. I do not ſee but that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſon and meere carnall man may bee grauelled, incumbred and diſquieted, in many circumſtances of carriage in this buſineſſe, but thoſe muſt bee debated and forethought before the entring therein, not repented of afterwards: If thou haſt laid thy hand to this Plow, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Huſbandman in this exerciſe, thou muſt not by any meanes looke backe, for then the allurement of other beauties will breed a diſlike of thine owne, in which that thou maiſt bee the better contented, haue ſome part in thine owne portion, for as the ſaying is:
<q>
                     <l>Who takes a woman foule vnto his wife,</l>
                     <l>Doth pennance daily, yet ſinnes all his life.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The charges of children, the vnfaithfulneſſe of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, the diſquietneſſe of neighbours, would wiſh for a former liberty and releaſement, and nothing diſgeſteth this courſe of life more then conſtancy and perſeuerance, and becauſe it is a Trade of ſuch Myſtery and Art, therefore (as a famous man of our time writeth) thoſe that haue but ſeuen yeares to learne any other, haue three
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13521:29"/>
times ſeuen to acquaint themſelues in the laborinth of this and the management thereof before they vndertake it, therefore hauing this notion make vſe thereof, either diſcharge it willingly and contentedly, or vndertake it not at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIIII. Certaine Precepts to be obſerued either in Wiuing or Marriage.</head>
               <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ooe not by Embaſſadour.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Make not thy friend too familiar with thy wife.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Conceiue not an idle iealouſy, being a fire once kindled not eaſily put out.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Affect him not that would ill poſſeſſe thee.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Blaſe not her beauty with thine owne tongue.</p>
               <p n="6">6 If thy eſtate bee weake and poore marry farre off and quickly; if otherwiſe firme and rich, at home and with deliberation.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Bee aduiſed before thou conclude, for though thy errour may teach thee wit it is vncertaine in this whether thou ſhalt euer haue the like occaſion to practiſe it.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Marry not for Gentility without her ſupport, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it can buy nothing in the Market without money.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Make thy choice rather of a vertuous then a learned wife.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Eſteeme rather what ſhee is of her ſelfe, then what ſhee ſhould bee by inheritance.</p>
               <p n="11">11 <hi>Intactam quaeris intactam eſto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bee that example to thy wife thou wouldſt haue her to imitate.</p>
               <p>For hee that ſtrikes with the Point muſt bee content to bee beaten with the Pommell.</p>
               <p n="12">12 Shee whoſe youth hath pleaſed thee diſpiſe not her age.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:13521:29"/>13 That thou maiſt bee loued, be amiable.</p>
               <p n="14">14 Saile not on this Sea without a good Compaſſe, for a wicked woman brings a man to repentance ſooner than a ſurfet, ſooner then ſuretiſhip.</p>
               <p n="15">15 'Tis the greater diſpraiſe to children to bee like to wicked parents.</p>
               <p n="16">16 'Tis more torment to bée iealous of a mans wife, then reſolued of her diſhoneſty.</p>
               <p>And the more miſery that a man may bee aſſured of her vice that way, but cannot bee of her vertue.</p>
               <p n="17">17 True chaſtity doth not onely conſiſt in keeping the body from vncleaneſſe, but in with-holding the minde from luſt; &amp; ſhe may be more maide that hath bene vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly forced thereto in body, then ſhee that hath barely conſented in heart.</p>
               <p n="18">18 A true wife ſhould bee like a <hi>Turcoyſe</hi> ſtone, cleere in heart in her huſbands health, and clowdy in his ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>And like a <hi>Tortoyſe</hi> vnder her ſhell euer bearing her houſe vpon her backe.</p>
               <p n="19">19 Deferre not thy Marriage to thy age, for a woman out of her owne choyce ſeldome pluckes a man, (as a Roſe) full blowne.</p>
               <p n="20">20 Marry ſo thy body that thou maiſt marry thy mind; which that thou maiſt the better do, thus meditate.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That if thou hadſt in variety of woman out-para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leld <hi>Salomon,</hi> thou ſhouldſt in the end giue vp thy verdict with his: <hi>That all is but vanity and vexation of Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 That it is in luſt as in riches, where to deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing and to inioy all things is but one: To vncouer more ſeuerall nakedneſſe then the Turke from his Decimary <hi>Seraglio</hi> hath authority for, with an vnſatiateillimited ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, and to deſire none, at leaſt wiſe no variety, is the ſame I with aduantage.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That if thou ſhouldeſt thus ſeeking to pleaſe thine appetite inioy a thouſand, and but want one thou deſireſt,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13521:30"/>
thou ſhouldſt more grieue for that little want, then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in all thy former plenty.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Then ſince what thou canſt enioy, conſume thy oyle to the ſocket, and thy ſubſtance to a morſell, will not, be one to thy pleaſure for ten thouſand that eſcape it, the variety ſo large neuer to bee gathered into one bundle of thy fruition, to ſet vp thy reſt, but the more thou purſueſt it the more thou art diſtracted: Content thy ſelfe within thy lawfull limits, and deſtroy not thy ſelfe to runne after that thou canſt nere oretake, which the faſter thou fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweſt it the ſwifter it flies from thee.</p>
               <p n="5">5 That it were a griefe to die for the full pleaſure of any ſence, but a torment for a taſt to a greater diſtemper, like to him that ſhould purchaſe at a deare rate ſalt water to quench his thirſt, which the more hee ſhould drinke ſhould but the more increaſe it.</p>
               <p n="6">6 That if beauty, or wiſedome, or any other portion of the body or minde aſſaile thée, refell them with this thought, that they are but ſhadowes of that ſubſtance, which ſhould the more allure thee: But pictures, which if they pleaſe, are but that the patterne ſhould be the more deſired.</p>
               <p>Thinke that as each day is an abridgement of all time, preſents the ſame light, the ſame vſe, the ſame Sunne and Firmament, and the ending of this renues but the ſame to morrow: So each woman an abridgement of that whole ſexe, and infirmity, how meane ſo euer, expreſſeth the ſame ſubſtance, the ſame mould, and mettall, propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, quality, and vſe of all other in the world: Who then would be ſo mad againſt ſence, though they would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade otherwiſe by Title, by Trapping, by copious adulterating all partes, to beleeue (as they would bee thought) that they are other then what they are, other then the ſame, vnleſſe worſe then other: The ſame way and the ſame faſhion, leading to the Harborough of the ſame ſite, of the ſame condition and quality, though a
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13521:30"/>
little more circumſtances (in ſome then other) beates the Buſh, and vſhers it on. Know this, that the end of all ſuch variety is no more then one diſh, dreſſed and preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a ſeuerall Cooke, and faſhion the ſame in all one but in circumſtance and carriage: Who would thus bee mad without reaſon to ioyle after the whole Alphabet of woman, when the leſt letter in the row expoundeth all that Text and Couerture. And for Title, or Toombe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like brauery, well may they worke vpon the eie of follie but neuer beſiege the heart of vnderſtanding: And as it was lately well obſerued by one, who, to that effect, thus further noted their vanity.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Things were firſt made, then cal'd, woman the ſame,</l>
                  <l>With or without falſe Title, or proud name.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And if this bee not yet enough, take with thee beſides for a concluſion and barre to all the reſt, this Motto or Sentence to leade thee home: that,
<q>
                     <l>Since all earths pleaſures are ſo ſhort and ſmall,</l>
                     <l>The way to enioy moſt is to abiure them all.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Diſcontents in all Ages, Sexes, States, Conditions.</head>
               <l>VNmedled ioyes here to no man befall,</l>
               <l>Who leaſt hath ſome, who moſt hath neuer all:</l>
               <l>I haue examin'd from the King on's Throne,</l>
               <l>To him that at his chayned Oare doth groane,</l>
               <l>Euery eſtate, condition, and degree</l>
               <l>Scytuate betweene this large extremitie:</l>
               <l>Yet whereſoeuer that I caſt mine eye,</l>
               <l>I neuer was ſo fortunate to ſpye</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:13521:31"/>That man that had ſo great a bleſſing lent him,</l>
               <l>That had not ſome what in't to diſcontent him:</l>
               <l>The rich man with his cares and feares oppreſt</l>
               <l>In all hee hath can finde but little reſt:</l>
               <l>Ill Creditors, vnthrifty Heyres, and loſſes,</l>
               <l>Or elſe the Gout, or ſomething worſe, all croſſes.</l>
               <l>The poore in want forſaken of his friends,</l>
               <l>Thinkes that were wealth is there all ſorrow ends:</l>
               <l>But yet as here immediately I ſhow,</l>
               <l>The rich that hath it doth not finde it ſo.</l>
               <l>One Tradeſman he diſlikes his owne Vocation</l>
               <l>And on a worſe he ſets his admiration.</l>
               <l>The ſingle man commends the married life</l>
               <l>That hath the ſweete fruition of a wife:</l>
               <l>That opens all her beauties and her treaſure,</l>
               <l>In Hils and Dales that he ore-walkes at pleaſure:</l>
               <l>That may vnſtarted and vnfear'd pertake</l>
               <l>Whole nights together, that which he doth quake</l>
               <l>To ſnatch in corners, when he muſt away,</l>
               <l>Sometimes diſturb'd when he would longer ſtay:</l>
               <l>Banniſh't like Tantalus in his forc'd haſt,</l>
               <l>To touch the ſweeteneſſe that he may not taſte.</l>
               <l>The married man whom all theſe danties cloy</l>
               <l>Thinkes that the ſauce the ſweetneſſe doth deſtroy:</l>
               <l>And that to purchaſe is ſo wondrous deere,</l>
               <l>That he had rather faſt then finde the cheere.</l>
               <l>Then children come, and they augment his charges,</l>
               <l>And iealouſie ſome times all theſe inlarges.</l>
               <l>That what th'other thinkes doth heauen excell</l>
               <l>He that inioyes it findes it but a hell:</l>
               <l>And wiſheth now, but that it is too late,</l>
               <l>That with the Batchelour he might change his ſtate.</l>
               <l>Therefore me thinkes his application fit</l>
               <l>That to a publicke feaſt compared it.</l>
               <l>Where thoſe that long haue ſate and cloy'd with meate,</l>
               <l>Would faine riſe vp as others faine would eate.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:13521:31"/>Th'ambitious youth leaſt folly ouerſway him,</l>
               <l>Hath Tutors, rod, and parents eye to ſtay him:</l>
               <l>Noting the liberty of riper yeares,</l>
               <l>With more impatience his reſtrainings beares:</l>
               <l>When elder times againe (the more 'tis ſtrange)</l>
               <l>Would faine creepe backe againe and with him change.</l>
               <l>The buſy Lawyer beating of his braine</l>
               <l>To make rough points by praeſidences plaine:</l>
               <l>Who from a iudgement wrongfully gone out,</l>
               <l>Doth ſometimes bring anothers right in doubt</l>
               <l>By iudging by it, let the firſt but ſtray</l>
               <l>And all go wrong that are adiudg'd that way.</l>
               <l>Noting the Marchant, how from forraine ſhores,</l>
               <l>The winds and waues land wealth vnto his dores:</l>
               <l>That where he ſleepe, or wake, or reſt, or play,</l>
               <l>So Aires be proſperous, he growes rich that way,</l>
               <l>Diſlikes his choyce, the Marchant he in danger,</l>
               <l>T'whom Rockes, and Shelues and Pyrates are no ſtranger:</l>
               <l>That try the wonders of the vnknowne deepes,</l>
               <l>Whom but a three inch't board from danger keepes:</l>
               <l>Traffiques with vnknowne Aires, and vnknowne friends</l>
               <l>Leauing his wife at home to doubtfull ends.</l>
               <l>VVho in his watry Pilgrimage is ſed</l>
               <l>To be with neither liuing nor the dead.</l>
               <l>Commends the Lawyer that hath power and skill,</l>
               <l>Either to make or marre, to ſaue or ſpill</l>
               <l>A mans whole reuenue, and therefore need</l>
               <l>Either for ſpeech or ſilence to be feede.</l>
               <l>The Empericke vncredited that tugges,</l>
               <l>VVith forceleſſe hearbes and with effectleſſe drugges,</l>
               <l>Commends the Church-man for his happy ſhare,</l>
               <l>Securely free'd from Temporary care:</l>
               <l>VVhen he againe with diſcontents full many,</l>
               <l>Thinkes the Phyſitians happieſt life of any;</l>
               <l>For by how much the bodies better deem'd,</l>
               <l>Then is the ſoule, ſo much more he's eſteem'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:13521:32"/>VVhich is by much, for let the body grieue it</l>
               <l>There's nothing vnattempted may relieue it:</l>
               <l>But for the ſoule although it die and languiſh</l>
               <l>VVee nere regard the dolor nor the anguiſh:</l>
               <l>But to the greateſt danger do reply</l>
               <l>It will recouer, or it cannot die:</l>
               <l>Therefore to him that doth the Phyſicke bring,</l>
               <l>To this regardleſſe diſeſteemed thing,</l>
               <l>Hath a poore meed more recompenc't his merite,</l>
               <l>That cures the body then applies to th'ſpirit.</l>
               <l>And what in health men graple and retaine,</l>
               <l>If ſickeneſſe come it flies to eaſe their paine.</l>
               <l>He that by auarice and damn'd extortion,</l>
               <l>Hath heap't vp many a pound to his heyres portion,</l>
               <l>So far from thought of doing any good,</l>
               <l>That what it was hee neuer vnderſtood;</l>
               <l>Sets vp his reſt for euer here to dwell,</l>
               <l>And therefore thinkes no other heauen or hell.</l>
               <l>Yet when this Seriant death comes to aſſayle him,</l>
               <l>To thee he opens hoping thou canſt bayle him:</l>
               <l>And though thou canſt not, do but ſeeme to aſſent,</l>
               <l>And he'le reward thee to thine owne content:</l>
               <l>Therefore this Art and Trade who ere neglect it,</l>
               <l>Let him exchange with me that do affect it:</l>
               <l>He that a weary languiſht youth hath lead</l>
               <l>To thinke what pleaſures are in Marriage bed:</l>
               <l>That hath entreated houres and yeares to haſt them,</l>
               <l>To cancell bonds that he may come and taſte them.</l>
               <l>VVhen there arriu'd not finding to content him,</l>
               <l>VVhat expectation did before preſent him.</l>
               <l>Let him appeaſe his thoughts vpon this ground,</l>
               <l>That in this world that purchaſe is not found.</l>
               <l>There's diſcontent in euery ſect and age,</l>
               <l>As well in Child-hood as in Parentage.</l>
               <l>There's diſcontent in euery mans Vocation,</l>
               <l>Therefore purſues it newneſſe innouation.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:13521:32"/>There's diſcontent from Scepter to the Swaine,</l>
               <l>And from the Peaſant to the King againe.</l>
               <l>Then whatſoeuer in thy will afflict thee,</l>
               <l>Or in thy pleaſure ſeeme to contradict thee;</l>
               <l>Giue it a welcome as a wholeſome friend,</l>
               <l>That would inſtruct thee to a better end:</l>
               <l>Since no Condition, Sect, nor State is free,</l>
               <l>Thinke not to find in this what nere can bee.</l>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
